<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The dying mans destiny, and the living mans duty, opened. And applyed in a sermon preached on board the Loyal-Eagle, upon the coast of Cormodell in the East-Indies. At the solemn obsequies of Mr. Richarde Bernard, Chyrurgeon, who, at the conclusion of it, was (with universal sorrow) thrown into the sea, Feb. 1. 1680. Together, with an elegy on his death. By C.N. Minister of the same ship.</title>
            <author>Nicholets, Charles.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 120 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52287</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N1087</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R222287</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833470</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833470</idno>
            <idno type="VID">37946</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52287)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 37946)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1783:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The dying mans destiny, and the living mans duty, opened. And applyed in a sermon preached on board the Loyal-Eagle, upon the coast of Cormodell in the East-Indies. At the solemn obsequies of Mr. Richarde Bernard, Chyrurgeon, who, at the conclusion of it, was (with universal sorrow) thrown into the sea, Feb. 1. 1680. Together, with an elegy on his death. By C.N. Minister of the same ship.</title>
                  <author>Nicholets, Charles.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>49, [1] p.,   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Dorman Newman at the Kings arms in the Poultrey,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLXXXII. [1682]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>C.N. = Charles Nocholets.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Funeral sermons --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:37946:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Dying Mans Deſtiny, AND THE Living Mans Duty, OPENED.</p>
            <p>And Applyed in a SERMON PREACHED On Board the <hi>Loyal-Eagle,</hi> upon the Coaſt of <hi>Cormodell</hi> in the <hi>Eaſt-Indies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At the <hi>Solemn Obſequies</hi> of Mr. <hi>Richard Bernard,</hi> Chyrurgeon, Who, at the Concluſion of it, was (with univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Sorrow) thrown into the SEA, <hi>Feb.</hi> 1. 1680.</p>
            <p>Together, with an <hi>ELEGY</hi> on his Death.</p>
            <p>By <hi>C. N.</hi> Miniſter of the ſame SHIP.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Dorman Newman</hi> at the <hi>King <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap>rm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> in the <hi>Poultrey,</hi> MDCLXXXII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:37946:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:37946:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Eccleſiaſt.</hi> the <hi>12th.</hi> ver. the <hi>5th.</hi> Becauſe Man goeth to his Long Home, and the Mourners go about the Street.</head>
            <p>SO woful is the Corruption of Man, by Original Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; that the whole of him is vitiated, and he totally in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capacitated, either for proſecuting the great end of his Creation, or for enjoying the great good, unto which he was Created. The end of his Making was the honour of his Maker; whoſe Will was the firſt of Cauſes, and whoſe Glory was the laſt of Ends. And for the accompliſhing ſo great an End, he was endued with faculties which truly eno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled him, with an underſtanding that highly advanced him, even to a degree a little below Angels; with a Majeſtick-Soveraignty, which crowned him with glory and dignity above all the other In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the Univerſe. But the Current of theſe Faculties is now changed, the ſtrength of this Underſtanding is now weakned, the glory of this Majeſty is now eclipſed, and Man is become a poor abject, inconſiderable, nothing; nothing Creature, unable to ſerve God, his higheſt End; and to enjoy God, his chiefeſt Good. He can do nothing now, but commit iniquity; nor pleaſure him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with the Poſſeſſion of any thing, but Vanity. The poyſon of Sin hath ſo invenom'd, enfeebled, and wholly altered him; that he can neither perform any duty to God, or (with any ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) receive mercy from God. Oh! How bitter were the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Comforts to him in the day of his fall, when he could no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſhine in that ſphere he was created in, nor be doing that work he was created for: Then, Oh then, the pleaſant walks of <hi>Edens</hi> Garden were too hot to hold him; and the fragrant Roſes of that Terreſtial Paradiſe were too prickly for him. And no wonder the Creature could afford him no Comfort, when his Sin-ſick-ſoul was uncapable of receiving any from the Creator. The Fountain of Light was more terrible to him, than the blackeſt Miſts of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; the Father of Mercies more affrightning, than the Compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:37946:3"/>of all Miſeries; for ſo we are told, he was <hi>Afraid of God, and went and hid himſelf in the Garden.</hi> In this forlorn condition is all the Poſterity of Man, till they come to the ſaving knowledge of Jeſus Chriſt; who, as a Brother, was born for the day of Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity to them? by whom they muſt be formed into the New-Birth, and ſo be brought ſpiritually to ſerve God, and to enjoy God in the State of Regeneration, whom they could never know in a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural condition.</p>
            <p>But that which renders Man yet more deſpicable; more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible, is, that ſince the Fall, he not only fails, and pitifully falls ſhort of Theologicals; but he is maimed, and extreamly er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous, even in Naturals: that is, he cannot keep from extreams in any viciſſitudes and changes he may go thorow, in any circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances he may be under, though contrary to the dictates of his own Reaſon. Hence, he cannot enjoy Mercies without ſlighting them, or placing his whole happineſs in them. He cannot feel Judgments without being hardned, as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> was; or filled with deſpair, as <hi>Cain</hi> was. He cannot love objects that ſafely and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocently may be beloved, without being weary of them, or too much over-prizing them. He cannot Mourn at objects that really call for Mourning, without Stupidity, or an immoderate fluctuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Sorrow. Now the golden Mean between the extream of the latter, as it is that implicit deſign of the words I have read unto you; ſo it ſhall be the main ſcope and drift of my following Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe among you; and I doubt not, but to make it evident, that the practical Part of this, is no leſs the Duty, than the Glory of every wiſe Man: which although it cannot, be attained to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome difficulty, yet it ought to be ſtudiouſly indeavoured after, by every one of us that pretend to Chriſtianity; that when we ſee Men go to their <hi>Long Home,</hi> we may with Religious Prudence, know how to act the part of <hi>Mourners</hi> in the <hi>Street.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall not trouble you with any Relative Conſideration of theſe words, or any Analitical Explication of the Chapter in which they are. Though the Preachers moſt elegant, and tropical Remarks on the Organical parts of Man's life, highly deſerve a ſerious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>view. If I had time (or were ſpirited) to make inſpection into them. But alas! I can better ſigh than ſpeak, and far more eaſily pour out floods of tears, than expreſs any fluency of words. I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Preached upon a more ſad occaſion, nor never was ſo wholly
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:37946:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>indiſpoſed for an Oratour as now. My Harp is turned into Mourning, and my Organ into the Voice of them that Weep. And therefore I hope you will pardon my impoliteneſs, and excuſe my abſurd tranſition from the Context, to the Text: In which (without any farther Preface) be pleaſed to obſerve.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> The Dying Man's Deſtiny, expreſſed,—<hi>Becauſe Man goeth to his Long Home.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> The Living Man's Duty, implyed,—<hi>And the Mourners go about the Street.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>From both theſe I ſhall infer this Concluſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doct.</hi> When Man goeth to his <hi>Long Home;</hi> (that is, when he dyeth, and is put in the <hi>Grave</hi>) there is a Mourning due from his Survivers, and ought, eſpecially, to be paid by thoſe that are near to him, and do behold him.</p>
            <p>It will not be incongruous, if we take a little notice of the <hi>Peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſis</hi> here in the Text, of <hi>Man's Dying,</hi> it is called a going to his <hi>Long Home. In locum ſeculi ſui, unto the place of his time;</hi> So <hi>Junius</hi> reads the words, that is, He goeth to the <hi>Grave,</hi> where he muſt remain a great deal of time; which is all one with our Tranſlation, that calls it, <hi>His Long Home.</hi> Now, the <hi>Grave</hi> is a <hi>Long Home.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt, <hi>Comparatively;</hi>
               </hi> or with reſpect to our ſojourning, and abiding here in this World. The time of the Bodies being in the Soul (for ſo our modern and beſt Philoſophers have choſe rather to expreſs it, than to ſay the Soul is in the Body) is but a very ſhort ſpace. One of the Antients was ſo affected with the ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Man's abode, in this vale of Tears, that he was at a ſtand, whether he ſhould call his life, <hi>Vitam morientem aut mortem viven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem; A dying Life, or a living Death.</hi> Indeed the Arithmetick of Man's time, in Scripture, is very ſmall: If we conſider his Years, they ſeldom exceed <hi>Fourſcore;</hi> yet then, is his ſtrength labour and ſorrow; he is ſoon cut off, and he flies away. If we reduce theſe years into days, we are told, <hi>Man that is Born of a Woman, is of few dayes, and full of trouble.</hi> Oh! But when the Marriage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knot between the Soul and Body is diſſolved, when there is a Writ of Divorce iſſued from the Court of Heaven to ſeparate them; then the Body is laid up in the <hi>Grave,</hi> and there it remains
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:37946:4"/>a long, long time, even till the day of the Reſurrection. The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſpeaks of an Home in this World, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. <hi>ver.</hi> 6. <hi>There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we are always confident, knowing that whilſt we are at Home in the Body, we are abſent from the Lord,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: The Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> here, I conceive, might be better rendred <hi>with,</hi> than <hi>in,</hi> and ſo the Sence will be (ſuppoſing it, as indeed we muſt, the Breathings of the Spirit of Man) we are here as ſtrangers, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journing or dwelling with the Body, as though we were at Home for a ſmall time. The Superſicies of the Earth, is Man's <hi>Short Home;</hi> the Bowels of it, is his <hi>Long Home.</hi> Now, if we compare the time of the longeſt-lived-man that ever was upon the Earth (which was <hi>Methuſelah,</hi> whoſe days amounted to <hi>Nine Hundred, Sixty, and Nine</hi> Years) with the time that he hath ſince lived in the <hi>Grave;</hi> we ſhall find the <hi>Grave</hi> to be his <hi>Long Home,</hi> in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of the Earth, notwithſtanding his days were lengthened ſo exceedingly upon it. Thus you ſee, the <hi>Grave</hi> is a <hi>Long Home, Comparatively.</hi> But,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The <hi>Grave</hi> is a <hi>Long Home, Really</hi> and <hi>Poſitivily.</hi> The Time of Man's commoration in this dark Manſion, is not for days, or years, but ages; yea, for many ages: So that, we may call it a ſmall Branch of the vaſt Ocean of Eternity. If we look at <hi>Abel,</hi> the firſt Lord of this <hi>Mannor;</hi> the firſt that took Poſſeſſion of this retired Place; how many Thouſand Years hath he kept houſe in this gloomy Tabernacle of the <hi>Grave:</hi> It hath been a long, a very <hi>Long Home</hi> to him. The <hi>Grave</hi> hath been an inhabited Tenna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by <hi>Adam</hi>'s poſterity, above Five Thouſand Years. And we that are yet alive, waiting to go down into it; how long our a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bode may be in it, we are uncertain; becauſe, <hi>We know not in what day or hour the Son of Man ſhall come</hi> to break open the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon Doors of the <hi>Grave,</hi> and to ſet us at liberty, that are in the Priſon-Houſe. <hi>Job</hi> ſpeaks of the <hi>Grave,</hi> as the Houſe he was moſt certain to go unto, and take up his dwelling in, <hi>Chap.</hi> 30. <hi>vor.</hi> 23. <hi>For I know that thou wilt bring me to Death, and to the Houſe appointed for all Living.</hi> It is an Houſe of a long ſtanding, and will be of long duration, even as long as time it ſelf; it runs parallel with it. The Creation of the World, and the Reſurrection of Man out of the <hi>Grave,</hi> are the two Tropicks of time; or the ſacred boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daries that Heaven hath put to it; <hi>A parte poſt &amp; a parte ante,</hi> as the <hi>Philoſopher</hi> ſpeaks: For, as before the former it had no Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtence;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:37946:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſo, after the latter, it ſhall have no longer continuance, but be ſwallowed up in the fathomleſs Gulph of Eternity. Time that now is always running. <hi>Mob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>li curſu,</hi> with a ſwift pace, will then be ſtopt in its motion, and be no more. But there are ſeveral things that muſt precede this: Great and weighty Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters muſt be brought about by the hand of Divine Power, before the End cometh; as we may plainly ſee, if we conſult the ſacred Oracles. Anti-chriſt muſt be brought down, with all his Uſurpati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Idolatrys. The <hi>Jews</hi> muſt be converted. The number of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> muſt be brought in; and the Houſe of the Lord muſt be ſet upon the Mountains, and exalted above the Hills, that all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions may flow unto it: For out of <hi>Zion</hi> ſhall go forth the Law, and the Word of the Lord from <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> But till this be done, the <hi>Grave</hi> is the appointed houſe for all Living; and therefore it is a <hi>Long Home.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having thus conſidered the <hi>Grave,</hi> as to its <hi>Duration;</hi> It is a <hi>Long Home:</hi> We will now ſpeak a little of the <hi>Grave,</hi> with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to its <hi>Qualification,</hi> what kind of <hi>Home</hi> it is: In the general, it is Man's deſigned and appointed <hi>Home.</hi> In the Text but now quoted out of <hi>Job,</hi> it is ſaid, to be the Houſe appointed for all Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving. God hath appointed (by a decree like the Laws of the <hi>Medes</hi> &amp; <hi>Perſians,</hi> which never can be changed or revoked) that the <hi>Grave</hi> ſhall be the one Repoſitory for all the Carcaſſes of <hi>Adams</hi> Children, to be laid up in, and kept till the day of the Reſurrection. The Apoſtle ſpeaks of the appointment of Death, (<hi>Heb.</hi> 9. <hi>ver.</hi> 27) <hi>And as it is appointed unto Men, once to Dye, but after this, the Judgment.</hi> Men are appointed to Dye, that they may go to their appointed home, the <hi>Grave.</hi> God hath appointed Mans being, and the time of his being in this World, as <hi>Job</hi> ſtedfaſtly believed. <hi>All the days of my appointed time will I wait, till my change come.</hi> And he hath appointed Man a place of reſting, after he goes out of this World, and that is the <hi>Grave:</hi> Oh! How ſhould this ſuppreſs Fears, and baniſh Cowardiſe from the Hearts of all timorous Chriſtians, that are ſlaviſhly afraid of the Paleneſs of Death, and tremble to think of going down into the darkneſs of the <hi>Grave:</hi> Why, Sirs, though it be never ſo dark and gloomy; though it be an houſe of Rotter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, a place of Putrefaction; it is the home prepared and appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by our Heavenly Father for us. And therefore, Why ſhould we ſcruple to lye down in it? Or, why ſhould we have any fearful
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:37946:5"/>apprehenſions about it? Such perſons and loſe all the comfort of their lives, as an Heathen well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved,</p>
            <q>Qui metuit Mortem, quod vivit perdit id ipſum.</q>
            <p>Oh! We ſhould be always remembring it, and reſt ſatisfied in it, that the Wiſe, the Righteous, the Holy, the bleſſed GOD hath appointed the <hi>Grave</hi> for our <hi>Long Home.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> God hath appointed die <hi>Grave,</hi> as Man's proper, ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble home; the home that doth naturally ſuite with his Complexion and Conſtitution. When <hi>Adam</hi> (by his Rebellion) had ſhaken off the glorious Theocraſy he was under, which would aſſuredly have protected him from the power of Death; however Homogeneal to his body, by reaſon of the contrariety of qualities in it; God left him (and that juſtly) to <hi>Fall,</hi> to <hi>Dye,</hi> according to the periſhing nature of that matter of which his Body was compoſed, (<hi>Gen.</hi> 3. <hi>ver.</hi> 19.) <hi>In the ſweat of thy Face ſhalt thou eat bread, till thou return unto the ground; for out of it waſt thou taken: for duſt thou art and unto duſt ſhalt thou return.</hi> As if he had ſaid; Hadſt thou con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in thy Obedience, and hadſt kept thy ſelf in thy Innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, ſitting under the ſhadow of my immediate Government; I would (by my Almighty Power) have preſerved thy Body (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding its Materiality) from ever ſeeing corruption, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the leaſt tainted with putrefaction. But now I'le leave thee to go down to the caverns of the Earth (where thy Body, being duſt, naturally inclines) with as much propenſity, as the Stone to its Center, or the touched Needle to the <hi>North-pole.</hi> What place ſo mete, what home, ſo proper for the earthly Tabernacle of of Mans body, as the earthly Apartments in the <hi>Grave:</hi> Indeed the <hi>Grave</hi> is no proper Home for the Soul (the better part) of Man; becauſe it is immaterial, incorporeal; not ſubject to deaths Soveraignity, aiming at a future being; and capable of being crowned with the glorious Diadem of everlaſting Honour; accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Sence of that famous <hi>Pagan.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Terra Domus non eſt animis accomoda noſtris,</l>
               <l>Alrius it noſtrae conditionis honor.</l>
            </q>
            <p>The <hi>Grave</hi> is alſo a proper Home for the Body, by reaſon of the great change Death makes in the Body; which renders it wholly unfit to continue upon the Earth, without intolerable and inſupportable offence to the Living. When Death hath ſerved
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:37946:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>his Writ of Arreſt, and fixed the Impeſſion of his cold hand; Oh! how miſerably is the faireſt Face then disfigured, how pittifully is the ſweeteſt Countenance then changed; how horridly is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleateſt Body then corrupted, and become a noiſom ſpectacle to its neareſt Relations? Inſomuch, that the fondeſt Husband then abominates the preſence of his moſt amiable Wife; the tendereſt Father then loaths the ſight of his moſt beloved Child; the deareſt and moſt intimate Friend, then ſtands aloof off from him, whoſe company was once truly precious, and acceptable to him. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Grave</hi> is the propereſt home for the breathleſs-body of Man; for there it ſleeps, and reſts without offence to any.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> God hath appointed the <hi>Grave,</hi> as Man's fixed ſetled home; a place of reſt after his toſſings, and hurryings to and fro in the World. We are born to Dye; yea, we begin to Dye as ſoon as we are delivered out of our Mothers Womb:</p>
            <q>Naſcentes Morimur, finiſque ab origine pendet.</q>
            <p>And we muſt expect no quiet, till Death concludes the play of our lives. The Apoſtle tells us, that here we have <hi>no continuing City,</hi> but we <hi>ſeek one to come.</hi> Indeed (like <hi>Noah</hi>'s Dove) we ſcarce know where to reſt the Sole of our Foot in peace. Here we are often forc'd to be moving, and removing, from one habitation, to another, from one country to another; yea from one end of the earth to the other; we are never fixed, nor throughly ſetled till we come to the <hi>Grave;</hi> and then there will be an end, for ever, of all our Wandrings, and weary ſome Pilgrimages. Man (whilſt travelling in the Regions of Mortallity, under the circumſtances of being obnoxious to divers contingencies) may, not unfitly, be compared to a Ship, under ſail, in the wide Ocean; for that he is always rowling and tumbling, beaten up and down with Winds, and Waves of various providencies, and fatal accidentalities that do attend him; and ſo continually upon the Surfe of Motion; that he never drops Anchor, never is at quiet till warped into the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of the <hi>Grave:</hi> And then, Oh then he is faſt, and rides ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure from all Storms and Tempeſts! For there the wicked ceaſe from troubling. and there the wearied are at reſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> God hath appointed the <hi>Grave,</hi> as Man's bounded, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined home. The place where all his deſires after, and all his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours for the enlargement of worldly poſſeſſions, will have their termination. Whilſt Man is upon the Earth, he is unſatiable in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:37946:6"/>his coveting earth, and thinks he hath never enough of it. His heart is like the daughter of the Horſe-leech, ſtill crying, <hi>Give, give;</hi> and is never ſatisfied. As <hi>Juvenal</hi> ſpeaks of <hi>Alexander:</hi>
            </p>
            <q>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o juveni vix totus ſufficit orbis.</q>
            <p>The whole World was not enough to quench the thirſt of his ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Humour; yea ſome ſay, he Wept, becauſe there were no more worlds to Conquer. Oh! But when he comes to the <hi>Grave,</hi> he is then confined to his breadth and length, and uncapable of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring any more; he is then bounded in his dimentions, without a thought of any enlargement. When we ſee the moſt covetous, or ambitious Man, going to the <hi>Grave;</hi> we may ſee, <hi>in tanto,</hi> a ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling of that Propheſy, <hi>That the loftineſs of Man ſhall be bowed down, and the haughtineſs of Man ſhall be brought low:</hi> (Though I know as to the full completion of it, it hath another tendency) for then his high Aſpirations, and all his vain Expectations are at a <hi>Ne plus ultra;</hi> and he confined to a narrow ſcantling of room in this <hi>Long Home.</hi> Oh! conſider this, you, whoſe greedy minds are never ſatisfied with terrene fruitions; but are always craving and graſping after more; that are contriving how to add <hi>houſe to houſe,</hi> and <hi>lay field to field, till there be no place;</hi> that are ſweating and toyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, journying and travelling, and taking a world of pains to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe the Store of your ſo much adored earthly Treaſure. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, I beſeech you, there is no buying or ſelling, no trading or traffiquing in the <hi>Grave:</hi> No bettering, or making finer or larger your accomodations there: The pooreſt <hi>Codrus</hi> hath as much room, as much conveniency in this dark Region, as the richeſt <hi>(Creſus.)</hi> For this is the <hi>Home</hi> where every Man hath e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to ſerve him, and is confined to the dimentions of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> God hath appointed the <hi>Grave,</hi> as Man's common, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidemical <hi>home.</hi> The place where all the Sons and Daughters of <hi>Adam</hi> muſt lye down together, of what nation or language, of what degree or quality ſoever they are. The ſmall and the great, the good and the bad are there: There is no diſtinction of perſons or conditions of men in that Climate. The moſt glorious Saint hath no more priviledge, or better entertainment in the <hi>Grave,</hi> than the worſt of Sinners. <hi>Job,</hi> though he was a good Man, one that put his whole truſt and confidence in God, &amp; one that was beloved of his God; and therefore aſcertain'd of his Souls poſſeſſing the Manſion of eternal Glory: yet as to his Body, he knew that muſt
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:37946:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>fare as the reſt of the world did. Hence we find him claiming kindred with the natives of that Country below, whither he was going: <hi>I have ſaid to corruption, thou art my Father, and to the worm, thou art my Mother and my Siſter.</hi> And again, <hi>Though after my skin worms deſtroy this body, yet in my fleſh ſhall I ſee God.</hi> Though he was ſo excellent a Saint, and had ſo pure a Soul; yet his Body was corruptible, and muſt become food for worms. We read of two (and but two) bodies of <hi>Adam</hi>'s Line, that were carried im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately from Earth to Heaven, without ſtopping at the <hi>Grave</hi> with the reſt of their Brethren: The one was <hi>Encch,</hi> of whom it is ſaid, <hi>He was not,</hi> for God took him: The other was <hi>Elijah,</hi> who who in a <hi>Chariot of Fire,</hi> with <hi>Fiery-horſes,</hi> was drawn up from beſide the River <hi>Jordan,</hi> to the New <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the holy Hill of <hi>Zion,</hi> to be for ever with God, and <hi>With the Spirits of juſt Men made perfect.</hi> The very Body of our <hi>Lord Jeſus</hi> (for the abſolute conquering of Death, and full compleating the work of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption) was neceſſitated to go down into the <hi>Grave;</hi> though not to corrupt and periſh there. For <hi>David</hi> perſonating him, thus prophetically ſpake—<hi>Thou wilt not leave my Soul</hi> (taken here figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratively for the outward Man) <hi>in Hell,</hi> (that is the <hi>Grave</hi> for ſo <hi>Sheol</hi> ſignifieth) <hi>Neither wilt Thou ſuffer thy holy One to ſee Corruption.</hi> Implying, that all other bodies muſt ſee corruption; under what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever circumſtances, they may be conſidered; when they come to this common <hi>home,</hi> this general receptacle of the <hi>Grave.</hi> For, as all muſt lye down, and take up their dwelling there together; ſo all muſt periſh, and rot, and be conſumed there; and that from the ſame cauſe, and after the ſame manner. The <hi>Grave</hi> is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <hi>home</hi> for the wicked in Judgment, it is their Jail, where they are kept ſafe till the great and general Aſſizes of the <hi>Day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> when the laſt <hi>Trumpet</hi> will ſound, and the <hi>Eccho</hi> of it will be heard from the one end of the Earth to the other, with this doleful Summons; <hi>Ariſe ye Dead, and come to Judgment.</hi> When the Viſion of <hi>John</hi> will be made good to a tittle; <hi>And I ſaw a great white Throne, and him that ſate on it, from whoſe Face the Earth and Heaven fled away, and there was found no place for them. And I ſaw the Dead, ſmall and great, ſtand before God, and the books were o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened; and another book was opened, which is the Book of Life, and the Dead were judged out of thoſe things that were written in the Book accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their Works. And the Sea gave up the Dead which were in it,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:37946:7"/>and Death and Hell</hi> (that is the Grave) <hi>delivered up the Dead which were in them, and thy were Judged every Man according to their Works.</hi> And the effect of this great Tryal, and dreadful Appearance, will be, the Bodies of the wicked ſhall be ſent to Hell, as well as their Souls, and be Tormented there for ever: God can, and for the glorifying of his Juſtice, he will Condemn both Body and Soul to Hell-fire at laſt. Thoſe Ears that have been always open to let in the Air of obſcenity, and tickled with delight in the helliſh mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick of prophane Language, ſhall then be terrified with the doleful <hi>Howlings, and Cryings, and Gnaſhing of Teeth,</hi> that will there be in an horrible manner among the wreached Miſcreants. Thoſe Eyes that have been as Windows to let in Luſt, and all manner of wantonneſs, and filthineſs into the Soul, ſhall then be puniſhed with beholding the ghaſtly Looks of affrightning Devils, that will be continually ſtaring the damned in the Face. Thoſe Tongues that have been the Bellows of the Devil, blown into from Hell, always imploy'd in belching forth horrid Oaths, blaſpheming their Creator; or thundring out direful Execrations, curſing the Creature; and that without either ſhame or remorſe ſhall then be miſerably ſcorched in that inextinquiſhable Fire, which there burneth Day and Night. In a word, thoſe Bodies that here have been veſſels of uncleaneſs, members of an harlot, recepticles of all prophaneſs, ſhall then be rowling on fiery Pillars in thoſe ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Burnings, in thoſe devouring Flames, which the Breath of the Lord hath kindled; when that amazing, and ſoul-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founding Sentence is pronounced upon them, by the Month of the righteous Judge himſelf, <hi>Depart from me ye Curſed, into ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Fire, prepared for the Devil and his Angels.</hi> But now the <hi>Grave</hi> is a common home to the Saints, and People of God in Mercy; it is the place where their Bodies are clarify'd, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined from all droſs and corruption, and ſo made fit for Glory. Oh! what a glorious Morning, what a joyful bleſſed day will that of the Reſurrection be, to All that ſleep in Chriſt: For then, with their bodily Eyes, ſhall they behold their Saviour, and in the re-union of their Bodies, with their Souls, ſhall they be for ever with him; hearing him ſpeaking in that ſoul-revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, ſoul-refreſhing, yea, ſoul-raviſhing Language to them; <hi>Come ye bleſſed of my Father, inherit the Kingdom prepared for you, from the Foundation of the World.</hi> Then the Body, that is
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:37946:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>now <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a body of meanneſs; or a low abject vile Body, by reaſon of its corruption; ſhall in that day become <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a Body of Glory; for it will be changed, and made like unto the glorious Body of the Lord Jeſus, and in conformity to that Glory put on, <hi>Stolam immortalitatis<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of immortality.</hi> The dead bodies of Saints ſhall live; yea, together with the dead Body of Chriſt ſhall they ariſe: They ſhall awake, and ſing, though now they dwell in the Duſt; for their Dew, is as the <hi>Dew of Herbs;</hi> and the Earth ſhall give them up as the <hi>Lord's Dead.</hi> Now then, if the <hi>Grave</hi> be Man's proper home, his ſeltled home, his confined home, and his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon home: Ah! How ſhould all of us, whether rich or poor, high or low, old or young, be familiarizing this home to our ſelves, as that which we muſt all come to. Oh Sirs! Methinks you ſhould have ſerious and awful thoughts of your ghaſtly pale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, your loathſome blackneſs, and your habitations in the dark. And ſo I paſs from the <hi>Dying Mar's Deſtiny—He goes to his Long Home: To the Living Man's Duty</hi>—He ought to be a <hi>Mourner in the Street:</hi> I told you, in the <hi>Doctrine,</hi> there was a <hi>Mourning,</hi> due from the <hi>Survivers,</hi> to the <hi>Deceaſed;</hi> I ſhall now labour to make it appear; and that upon a four-fould ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt, Naturally,</hi> There is a natural Obligation to <hi>Mourn,</hi> when any Man goes to his <hi>Long Home;</hi> and ſurely they are very unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural, that do not pay it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> For that, they that <hi>Live,</hi> are of the ſame Mould with them that <hi>Dye.</hi> All are made, and compoſed of the ſame pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing Earth. Hence <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks not only of himſelf, but of all Men, when he inſcribes <hi>Vanity</hi> on them, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 39. <hi>ver.</hi> 5, 6. <hi>Behold thou haſt made my Days as an hand's breath, and my Age is as nothing before Thee, verily every Man at his beſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate is altogether Vanity. Surely every Man walketh in a vain ſhow, ſurely they are diſquieted in vain; He heapeth up Riches, and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not who ſhall enjoy them.</hi> Here is a general Rule without any exception, that every Man, be he never ſo great, or high, or rich, or wiſe, or learned in the world; and that in his beſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, take him under what circumſtances you will, is <hi>Vanity;</hi> yea, altogether <hi>Vanity:</hi> a poor crazy, empty, evanid thing. Now, when Man, that is ſo vain, ſo periſhing in his own Nature, ſees one of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:37946:8"/>the ſame Mould, with himſelf, carrying to the <hi>Grave,</hi> to be placed in his <hi>Long Home;</hi> the Law of Nature exacts a tribute of Tears from him (though he had no particular acquaintance with, or obligation to the perſon deceaſed) becauſe he beholds a crumbling away, and a fading of that Earth, whereof himſelf is made; at which, Nature cannot but have a reluctancy, and vent its ſympathetical Paſſion. But as the Apoſtle ſpeaks of ſome Monſters in <hi>filthineſs,</hi> and <hi>uncleaneſs,</hi> that they did that which is <hi>againſt Nature;</hi> ſo we may ſee many ſo hardned in ſtupidity, that contrary unto nature, they are not affected with, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned at the Death, or going to the <hi>Grave,</hi> of almoſt any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> There is a natural Obligation on the Living to <hi>Mourn</hi> for the <hi>Dead;</hi> for that Death is the thing which every Man in the world hath deſerved; as being lineally deſcended from <hi>Adam,</hi> who brought Death into the World, and inſlaved not only him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but all his poſterity unto its power. So ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. <hi>ver.</hi> 12. <hi>Wherefore, as by one Man, Sin entered into the World, and Death by Sin, and ſo Death paſſed upon all Men, for that all have Sinned.</hi> Had <hi>Adam</hi> never ſinned, <hi>Adam</hi> had never dyed; but <hi>in illo die</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>in that day thou eateſt the Fruit thereof, thou ſhalt ſurely dye; or</hi> (as it is in the Original) <hi>dying, thou ſhalt dye.</hi> And indeed, as he devolved <hi>Guilt,</hi> ſo he entailed death (the ſad conſequence of that <hi>Guilt</hi>) upon all that ſhould come after him unto the end of the World. Oh! therefore, how natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral would ſuch a reflection as this be, at the news of any Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals fall by the ſtroke of Death, or at the ſight of any deceaſed per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, going to his <hi>Long Home.</hi>—I am a Child of <hi>Adam</hi> as well as he, and in the guilt and pollution of his original Diſobedience was I ſhaped, and ſubjected, to all the Miſeries that attended that ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, did my Mother conceive me, and bring me forth: And ſurely I have added to the ſtock of original Corruption, multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes, innumerable multitudes of actual Tranſgreſſions; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I have every way merited Death, and deſerved to be impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned in the Dungeon of the <hi>Grave,</hi> as much as he that hath paſt through it, and is gone down before me into it. Should not I then be concerned at, and deeply affected with what hath befallen him. The extremity of pain that he was in, the weary ſome nights that he enjoyed, the tumblings and toſſings that he under-went, the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:37946:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>bitter diſtreſs and anguiſh that poſſeſſed his Soul, which enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced thoſe doleful ſighs and ſobs, thoſe heart-fetcht-groans and ſhrikes from his dying Breaſt, are all things that I, in the ſame (if not in a greater) meaſure have deſerved. Oh! then that my <hi>Head were Waters,</hi> and my <hi>Eyes a Fountain of Tears,</hi> that I could mourn and weep, and truly lament at this <hi>Mournful</hi> Spectacle; and that from this conſideration, that as he (the object of Morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity before my Eyes) is deprived of life, and all the comforts of it; as he is ſnatcht away from all his Friends and Relations; as he (of a living Man) is become a lump of dead Clay, a piece of rotten putrifying Fleſh, fit for nothing but to feed worms in the <hi>Grave,</hi> even ſo have I moſt juſtly merited in the like manner to be; nothing hath befallen him, but what is due to me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> There is a natural Obligation on the <hi>Living</hi> to <hi>Mourn</hi> for the <hi>Dead,</hi> for that there is no living perſon, but muſt come to it himſelf. Death is a debt we muſt all pay to Nature. <hi>Job</hi> ſpeaks of Man indefinitely, thereby including every Man in what capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſo ever he is, <hi>Chap.</hi> 14. <hi>ver.</hi> 2. <hi>He cometh forth like a flower, and is cut down; he fleeth alſo as a ſhadow, and continueth not.</hi> And we are elſewhere told, that, <hi>All fleſh is graſs, and the glory thereof as the flower of the field; the graſs withereth, the flower fladeth;</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſo, when the Hand of God is upon Man, upon any Man; he maketh his Beauty to conſume away like a Moth; for that every Man is <hi>Vanity, Selah.</hi> We have an Interrogation concerning this, which implies a vehement Negation (for ſo the Scripture often expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth it ſelf) <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89. <hi>ver.</hi> 48. <hi>What Man is he that liveth, and ſhall not ſee Death, ſhall he deliver his Soul from the hand of the Grave, Selah.</hi> That is, there is no Man living, but muſt ſee Death, and come into the dominion of the <hi>Grave.</hi> Now, if Death be thus com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to every Man, then every Man ought certainly to be affected, when he ſees another under the power of it. Would it not I pray you, argue more than ordinary ſtupidity and ſenceleſneſs, in that Malefactor, that beholding a Partner in Guilt, and Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation with himſelf, dying a ſhameful painful Death, according to the Sentence of the Law; the which Death he himſelf muſt undergo the day following; and yet not to be concerned at ſuch a ſpectacle, ſo much as to ſhed a Tear, or manifeſt any meltings of Heart at ſo doleful a ſight. Oh! How unnaturally hard-hearted would you ſay this Man was. Why, Sirs, this is our very caſe; we
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:37946:9"/>are all real Malefactors before God, condemned by him to death, to the ſame death, and ſooner or later we muſt be laid on our ſick Beds, the common place of Execution; and when we ſee any in pain and miſery there before us: Oh! we ſhould remember it will be our turn ere long. Do we ſee a dying Man in a languiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing departing condition, fetching his laſt ſigh, heaving for his laſt groan, and giving up his laſt breath: Oh! we ſhould ſadly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect upon our ſelves, as that Father of whom I have read, did at the ſight of any Coffin—<hi>Ille hedie, ego cras. He is gone to day, and ſo may I to morrow,</hi> or to be ſure muſt go one day or other; then which, nothing is more certain.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> It is not corrupted, but refined Nature, that eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally enforces this duty of <hi>Mourning</hi> for the <hi>Dead;</hi> and the more Nature is purged, the more it is enlivened in the regular perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of this Work. We find the Spirit of God inciting, and calling upon Men ſolemnly to do it, <hi>Jer.</hi> 9. <hi>ver.</hi> 17, 18. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, Conſider ye, and call for the mourning Women, that they may come, and ſend for cunning Women, that they may come. And let them make haſt, and take up a wailing for us, that our Eyes may run down with Tears, and our Eye-lids guſh out with Water<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Why, What is the matter? what is the cauſe there ſhould be ſuch a great general Mourning? <hi>ver.</hi> 21. <hi>For Death is come up into our windows, &amp; is entered into our palaces, to cut off the Children from with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, and the young Men from the ſtreets.</hi> Oh! When Death is taking its range about the ſtreets, it is an eſpecial time for Mourners to be there; to manifeſt a real Mourning, under ſuch a diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; to put on Aſhes for Beauty, and inſtead of the Garment of Joy, to be cloathed with the Spirit of Heavineſs. Religion doth not hinder any natural act, it only regulates the mode, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines the end of the performance. It doth not hinder natural love, it only teacheth us how to love innocently; nor doth it hinder na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural ſorrow, it only guides us how to ſorrow profitably. As Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines ſay, Though <hi>Religion</hi> be above reaſon, yet it is not contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to reaſon; ſo though it be an enemy to all vitious, corrupt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of nature, yet it obligeth no perſon to be unnatural: that is, to fail in doing thoſe things which the principals of natural being do require, as neceſſary to the demonſtration of its being; but rather provokes to a lively, and regular doing of them. And ſurely this duty, under our preſent conſideration, is that which
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:37946:9"/>the ſpirit of a Man dictates to him, though in a dark miſtaken way; and the Spirit of God ſuggeſts to him, in a right, ſafe, juſtifiable way. That there is a time to <hi>Mourn,</hi> is paſt diſpute, ſince the Word of Truth ſpeaks it; and that a Funeral Solemnity (or ſeeing Man go to his <hi>Long Home</hi>) is ſuch a time, is alſo out of doubt, ſince the Word of Truth enjoyns it. Hence we may warrantably, and not uncharitably conclude, That Man, void of Reaſon or Religion, of Nature or Grace, yea of Love to God or Man, that brings not a Mourning-heart along with him to the <hi>Houſe of Mourning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly, <hi>Relatively;</hi>
               </hi> There is a relative obligation upon the living, to Mourn for the dead; which Relation, either in a more large or ſtrict ſence, takes in the whole Race of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> For that all men are related in <hi>Adam,</hi> as ſpringing from his Loyns. Though men are now diſtinguiſhed into many ſorts of Nations, and divers Kinds and Manners of perſons; yet they all come from the ſame Root, the ſame Off-ſpring; all Children of the ſame Father, of the ſame Mother: So we are told, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. <hi>ver.</hi> 20. <hi>And</hi> Adam <hi>called his Wives name</hi> Eve, <hi>becauſe ſhe was the Mother of all Living.</hi> All the vaſt numberleſs multitudes of People through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Univerſe, that have been, or ſtill are in the World, came originally from her Womb. She is the Parent from whence ſo many Millions of Souls may derive their pedigree. The higheſt, and moſt certain degree of Relation in natures Climax. Methinks then we ſhould not be ſo unmindful of our primitive Extraction, as to be wholly unconcerned at the departure of one of the ſame Race with our ſelves. There is none ſo remote from us in Country or Acquaintance, but he is near to us; yea, related to us, <hi>Secundum eſſe,</hi> as he is a Son of <hi>Adam.</hi> And can we afford never a tear, never a ſigh, never a compaſſionate ſob to accompany ſuch an one (be he who he will, or what he will) to his <hi>Long Home:</hi> Ah! 'Tis ſign we are hardned againſt our own Fleſh; and that we ſhamefully forget the Father that begat us, and the Mother of whom we are all Born. Oh! what a debauched, abominable Age do we live in; wherein Men are ſo ſenceleſs, and horridly ſtupid; ſo intoxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated with Luſts and Vanities, ſo bewitched to the Allurements of the World, &amp; ſo feared in their evil ways and courſes; that Death (though it be even at their doors) is diſregarded by them; and the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:37946:10"/>going to the <hi>Grave</hi> of others (though their very Neighbours) is a thing they take no notice of, nor in the leaſt <hi>Mourn</hi> for; ſo long as they have their ſtrength and health, to drink and ſwear, and indulge themſelves in their luſts and pleaſures; they care not who are Sick, or who Dye, or who go to the <hi>Grave,</hi> it is all one to them. Truly ſuch perſons are ſo far from being like Chriſtians, that they are ten thouſand times worſe than Heathens. Oh! how will the <hi>Egyptians</hi> riſe up in Judgment againſt the Men of this Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, and condemn them for their melting and mourning De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment at the Funeral of good old <hi>Jacob</hi> (notwithſtanding he was of another Nation and Religion) when they came to the Threſhing-floor of <hi>Arad,</hi> which is beyond <hi>Jordan;</hi> 'tis ſaid, they Mourned with a very great and ſore Lamentation: inſomuch, that the place was called <hi>Abel-Mizraim,</hi> the <hi>Mourning of the Egyptians.</hi> But ah! How little Mourning is there found amongſt us, upon ſuch occaſions!</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> As there is a Relation in the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> wherein all are concerned; ſo there is a Relation in the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> wherein not a few are tied, and obliged to be concerned one for another, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially at ſo great a change, as that of Death. Now this Relation, is either more Large, or more Strict: More Large; and ſo all, that own Jeſus Chriſt the Son of God, to be come in the Fleſh, are within the reach of it, who are therefore called by one general and Catholick name, <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> But more Strictly; and ſo it is reſtrained peculiar to Believers; who by the ſame work of Grace, are made true Members of the Church-militant, and by the ſame act of Faith, are expecting the glory of the Church-triumphant: Who are engaged in the ſame cauſe, Souldiers under the ſame Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, Wreſtlers againſt the ſame Enemy, even Principalities and Powers, and ſpiritual Wickedneſſes in high places: Who are ſighting the ſame Battle, Runners of the ſame Race, Purſuers after the ſame Crown, even that which is incorruptible, undefiled, that fadeth not away: Who are Inheritors of the ſame Promiſe, Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-heirs of the ſame Kingdom, Waiters for the ſame Adoption, to wit, the Redemption of the Body: Who are Profeſſors of the ſame Faith, Believers in the ſame Chriſt; Experiencers of the ſame happineſs in the glimpſes of <hi>Zion's</hi> glory, and the fore-taſte of the Joys, of the Life to come. In a word, who are under the ſame Tye, confirmed by the ſame Seals, bound by the ſame Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:37946:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>to live according to the Rule, and in the Fellowſhip of the Goſpel. This Relation is ſo near, ſo great, ſo obligatory, that the Apoſtle calls it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Brotherhood, or a compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of Brothers. As all Men are Brothers in <hi>Adam,</hi> naturally; ſo Believers are Brothers in Chriſt, ſpiritually; and this nearneſs in Relation, ſhould certainly cauſe a <hi>Mourning,</hi> when Death makes a Separation. Oh! when a Godly Man goes to his <hi>Long Home,</hi> then Godly-Mourning ſhould <hi>Go about the Streets;</hi> for that there is a great Loſs, and will be a real want of his Prayers, his Tears, his Holy Converſe, and the good he might farther have done in the World. Upon this account, <hi>Eliſhah</hi> Mourned for <hi>Elijah,</hi> and ſent his loud Acclamations of Sorrow to Heaven after him, when he was taken up from him—<hi>My Father, my Father, the Chariots of</hi> Iſrael <hi>and the Horſemen thereof.</hi> This made the <hi>Epheſians</hi> Mourn ſo dolefully at <hi>Paul</hi>'s departure, becauſe they were never to ſee him again. So ſaith the Text—<hi>And they all wept ſore, and fellon</hi> Pauls <hi>Neck and kiſſed him.</hi> Sorrowing moſt of all for the words that he ſpake, that they ſhould <hi>See his Face no more: Paul</hi> was their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Father, that had begotten them to God; and therefore they could not but <hi>Mourn,</hi> to think of parting with ſo dear a Relation; eſpecially ſince it was to be an eternal Farewel. How! muſt they never ſee his Face more; never hear the ſound of that golden Trumpet more, that had been ſo charming to their Ears; yea, ſo raviſhing to their Souls. Oh! This ſtrained up their Sorrow to the higheſt Peg; this made them <hi>Mourn,</hi> with a Mourning truly Mournful. And we read, <hi>Acts</hi> 8. <hi>ver.</hi> 2. <hi>And devout Men carried</hi> Stephen <hi>to his Burial, and made great Lamentation over him. Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> was their brother, and companion in the Faith, Patience, and Tribulation of the Goſpel; and therefore they looked on them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves obliged to <hi>Mourn bitterly,</hi> and <hi>Lament ſorely,</hi> when he went to his <hi>Long Home.</hi> But alas! there is little of this Sorrow in theſe days; wherein Iniquity doth ſo much abound, and the Love of ſo many waxes cold to every good Work. There is no <hi>Mourning</hi> in the Streets of our <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> no <hi>Lamenting</hi> in the City of our <hi>Zion,</hi> when the Godly Man ceaſeth, when the Faithful fail from among the Children of Men. The Prophets complaint was, verily never more juſt and pertinent, than now—<hi>The Righteous periſheth, and no Man layeth it to heart, and Merciful Men are taken away, none con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that the Righteous is taken away from the Evil to come.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:37946:11"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> There is a Relation by Affinity, which obligeth Men to <hi>Mourn</hi> at the Departure (or going to their <hi>Long Home</hi>) of any ſo Related to them. This Relation is by Marriage; or joyning Families that were remote, and wholly unacquainted by <hi>Hymens</hi> bands together. Thus <hi>Hamor</hi> and <hi>Shechem</hi> deſired, That them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and all their Citizens, might be Related to the Family of <hi>Jacob,</hi> when they communed with him in the Gate—<hi>Theſe Men are peaceable with us, therefore let them dwell in the land, and trade there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; for the land,</hi>—<hi>Behold, it is large enough for them, let us take their Daughters to us for Wives, and let us give them our Daughters.</hi> As if they had ſaid, Let us contract a Relation by making inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable Marriages; that ſo we may be near to them, and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter acquainted with them. And ſurely in the compaſs of this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, it ought to be a ſenſible Affliction, when Death is Marring the Glory of their Society, and breaking the Hedge of their Unity, by taking one away. This was the cauſe of the <hi>Mourning</hi> of <hi>Orpah,</hi> and <hi>Ruth,</hi> at the parting with their Mother <hi>Naomy,</hi> who was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed their Mother but by Marriage, <hi>Ruth</hi> 1. <hi>ver.</hi> 14. <hi>And they lift up their voice, and wept again; and</hi> Orpah <hi>kiſſed her Mother, but</hi> Ruth <hi>clave unto her.</hi> They could not think of a Farewel, without powering out floods of Tears. Nay, ſo ſtrong were <hi>Ruth</hi>'s Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, that when it came to the pinch, ſhe would not leave her; But was reſolved to accompany her in all her Travels and Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, whatever ſhe ſhould undergo, or meet with for it; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhe told her—<hi>Thy God ſhall be my God, and thy People ſhall be my People, where thou goeſt, I will go, where thou dyeſt, I will dye, and there will I be buried.</hi> Now, as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſayes—<hi>Go to the Aut thou ſluggard, conſider her ways, and be wiſe.</hi> So I ſay in this caſe, Go to this <hi>Moabitiſh</hi>-Woman, thou hard-hearted Chriſtian (that canſt with dry Eyes, and a ſottiſh Spirit, behold a Relation en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tombed in the Earth) conſider the depth of her Affection, the pureneſs of her Love, the tenderneſs of her Heart, and be Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly Wiſe in knowing how to carry it under a parting-diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Oh! remember that as there may be an innocent and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Mirth, when Relations firſt meet, to begin their acquaintance, or contract their proximity together; ſo there ought to be a <hi>Mourning</hi> in a moderate way, when there is any parting or ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration by the hand of Death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> There is a Relation by Conſanguinity, which not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:37946:11"/>obliges, but enforces Tears from the Eyes of all perſons (unleſs unnatural bruits) accompanying any ſo related to them, to their <hi>Long Home.</hi> This Relation comes not only by a general deducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from <hi>Adam,</hi> but by a more near and immediate alliance, and conjunction in Blood; whereby they become <hi>Bone of one Bone,</hi> and <hi>Fleſh of one Fleſh.</hi> Such is the Relation between Husband and Wife, Parents and Children, Brothers and Siſters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now what Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band can forbear Tears, when his dear Wife is ſnatched out of his Arms, by Death; when the delight of his Eyes is taken away with a ſtroak. Who can then but imitate affectionate <hi>Abram,</hi> of whom it is ſaid, <hi>Gen.</hi> 23. <hi>ver.</hi> 2. <hi>And</hi> Sarah <hi>dyed in</hi> Kiriath-Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba; <hi>the ſame is</hi> Hebron, <hi>in the land of</hi> Canaan, <hi>and</hi> Abram <hi>came to Mourn for</hi> Sarah, <hi>and to Weep for her.</hi> She was the companion of his youth, the wife of his delights; the mother of his <hi>Iſaac,</hi> yea the better half of himſelf; and therefore he could not but <hi>Weep,</hi> when ſhe was gone from him. What Wife can refrain <hi>Mourning,</hi> when her beloved Husband is going down into the ſhades of Death, and ſhe to be left a poor deſolate, diſconſolate Widow, as <hi>Naomi</hi> and her two Daughters in the land of <hi>Moab</hi> were: And how can poor Parents keep in Sorrow, when they ſee Death preying upon the Children of their Bowels, and confining their tender Limbs to the cold <hi>Grave.</hi> Hence we find <hi>David</hi> giving vent to his paſſion, for the Death of <hi>Abſolom,</hi> in this pathetical Exclamation, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18. <hi>ver.</hi> 33. <hi>And the King was much moved, and went up to the Chamber over the Gate, and wept: and as he went, thus he ſaid, O my Son</hi> Abſolom, <hi>my Son, my Son</hi> Abſolom, <hi>would God I had dyed for thee:</hi> O Abſolom <hi>my Son, my Son.</hi> Indeed Divines conjecture the reaſon of <hi>David</hi>'s ſo great <hi>Mourning,</hi> was the fear of <hi>Alſolom</hi>'s miſcarrying, as to his eternal State; his doubt that it was not well with his Soul; he dying in a ſtate of Rebellion, both againſt his earthly and heavenly Father. Though this might have ſome impreſſion on <hi>David</hi>'s Heart, yet queſtionleſs 'twas Nature it ſelf drew out his Sorrow, from this very conſideration, that he was his Son, and there needs no other to enforce a <hi>Mourning.</hi> From this ſprung that Voice of Lamentation, and Weeping, and great Mourning, which was heard in <hi>Ramah,</hi> poor <hi>Rachels</hi> pittifully Weeping for their Children, and refuſing to be Comforted, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were not.</hi> And then reciprocally, what Children can be ſo hard-hearted, ſo ſtony-ſpirited, as not to wait upon their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:37946:12"/>Coffins with Tears to the <hi>Grave.</hi> When <hi>Jacob</hi> was gathered to his Fathers, and had yielded up the Ghoſt in a good old Age, we read that his Son <hi>Joſeph</hi> fell upon his <hi>Face, and wept upon him, and kiſſed him.</hi> And truly this <hi>Mourning</hi> is but an expreſſion of Love; and where it is not, we may ſafely infer, that thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons had no love, no affection at all for their Relations, when a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly, <hi>Morally;</hi>
               </hi> There is an obligation (which none that pretend to any principles of Morality will diſown) upon the <hi>Living</hi> to Mourn for the <hi>Dead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> For that a Man is loſt by Death. As to the enjoyment of him, and ſociety with him, he is periſhed from among Men. Now Man being a ſociable, delightful Creature, the Loſs of him is conſiderable, and ought to be laid to heart, by all that ſurvive him. Man is to be lookt upon as the chief peice of Workmanſhip in the Creation; the glory of all the Works of God in the lower Region. So wonderfully was he made, ſo ſtrangely was he faſhio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, ſo excellently was he adorned, that the good Angels admired him, and the Bad envyed him; which was the occaſion of their Fall, as ſome learned Writers have ſuppoſed. And what God ſpeaks of forming the World in general, we way apply to the Creating of Man in particular; with reſpect to the excellency of the Work, when he was preſented on the Theatre of the World. How did the Morning Stars, in that day, ſing together, and how did all the Sons of God ſhout for joy. And ſurely the Diſſolution of Man affords as much cauſe of ſorrow, as his Making did of glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; eſpecially conſidering that it is in Scripture, called, a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying of him. <hi>Thou turneſt Man into deſtruction, and then thou ſayſt, Return again ye Children of Men.</hi> When Man is in the midſt of his honour, in the height of his glory, in the greateſt of his power; in a moment, in the twinckling of an Eye, he may be daſhed in pieces, and be deſtroyed from off the Earth; for by the blaſt of God he periſheth, and by the breath of his Noſtrils he is conſumed. One ſmall puff blows him away, and he is no more to be heard of, as though he had never been. And ſhould not this be matter of grief and lamentation to the Living, to ſee ſo excellent a Creature as Man, deprived of his Being, bereaved of his Breath, ſtript of his Enjoyments, and all his Glory to be laid in the Duſt. Ah! What Eye can behold ſuch a ſight, what Ear can hear of ſuch
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:37946:12"/>a thing, and not be deeply affected with it, and Heart-pricked with ſorrow at it. Oh! How was our bleſſed Lord Jeſus concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, how Mournfully was he touched, when he heard the tydings of <hi>Lazarus</hi> deceaſe, though he was determined, &amp; very well knew how to raiſe him up, and bring him to Life again. Pray hear what is ſaid of him, <hi>John</hi> 11. <hi>ver.</hi> 33. <hi>When Jeſus therefore ſaw her weeping, and the</hi> Jews <hi>alſo weeping which came with her, he groaned in the Spirit, and was troubled.</hi> Here are two words in the Greek, and both empha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; he <hi>roared,</hi> or <hi>cried</hi> out in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. That is, he Mourned inwardly, and Lamentably, at the loſs of <hi>Lazarus.</hi> Again, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, He vehemently troubled or diſturbed himſelf. He was mightily affected with the change Death had made in that Family, which he had ſo great and pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar a Love for. Our Saviour ſhewed this great example of Mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, that he might modeſtly, and moderately expreſs the ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Grief, which we ought to have at the departure of Man, from the Land of the Living.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> For that when a Man goes to his <hi>Long Home,</hi> all the pleaſure in his ſociety is dead with him; nothing remains of it, but the remembrance which ſerves only to aggravate, and heigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the Grief of the Surviver. 'Twas a true ſaying of one—<hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra ſecunda bonus ſocius.</hi> A good companion is as a proſperous Gale, carrying a Man pleaſantly, and with comfort, through the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſtuous Sea of this World. And again—<hi>Bonum ſodalitium op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timum ſolatium. Good Company is the beſt ſolace:</hi> Indeed, ſuitable <hi>ſociety</hi> is the comfort of Life, the improvement of parts, the joy of the Intellect, the only diſtinguiſhing Priviledge that gives the Preference to Men above Beaſts. Take away this, and what hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs is it to be a Man, or what is humane Life any thing to be accounted of. But when Man is dead, there can be no more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in him, or comfort received by <hi>ſociety</hi> with him. There is no converſe in the ſhades below, no interlocution in thoſe gloomy Regions. The Grave is a ſilent houſe, where the Eyes of all the Inhabitants are cloſed in the Duſt, and their Mouths filled with cold Clay. And therefore this ſhould cauſe <hi>Mourning in the Streets,</hi> when we ſee a Man going to his <hi>Long Home</hi> (eſpecially ſuch a Man whom we have had any intimacy with) becauſe we ſhall never have the opportunity of enjoying any pleaſant hours with him, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighting our ſelves in the Spiknard of his friendſhip, which was
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:37946:13"/>wont to ſend forth ſo fragrant a ſmell. We muſt then bid fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel to all diſcourſing upon any ſubject, to all adviſing about any difficulties, to all profiting by any Polemick Notions ſtarted and improved in an amicable way. In a word, we muſt bid an eternal Adieu to any pleaſure or ſatisfaction we received in communing with him, for we ſhall enjoy no more of it for ever. Oh! ſurely this cannot but cut deep in a generous Soul; this cannot but great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wound a ſpirit, whoſe thoughts are drained from the droſs of <hi>Plebeian</hi> converſation, that has any eſteem at all for the advantages of a rational Life. Upon this account it was, that the old Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet in <hi>Bethel,</hi> Lamented over the Man of God which came from <hi>Judah,</hi> who was ſlain by a Lyon, as he rode upon an Aſs in the High-way. He bitterly Bewailed, and Mourned for his Death, crying out—<hi>Ah! alas my Brother.</hi> As if he had ſaid, I have been extreamly refreſhed by thy company, in hearing the Word of the Lord from thy Mouth, concerning the deſtruction of the Prieſts that burn Incenſe upon the Altar, and the pulling down the Houſe of <hi>Jereboam.</hi> Oh! <hi>How have I been ſtrengthned in my Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, confirmed in my Faith, and the more reſolved in the Ways of God, by this thy Propheſy. But now thou art gone, I ſhall never have any more of this profitable and ſpiritual Diſcourſe with thee.</hi> This made him Weep over his torn Carcaſs, and bitterly Lament his untime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Fall, and to give a ſolemn Charge to his Sons, that when he was Dead, they ſhould Bury him in the Sepulchre wherein this Man of God was Buried, and lay his Bones cloſe by the Bones of this Prophet.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> For that when a Man <hi>Dyes,</hi> and goes to his <hi>Long Home,</hi> he is paſt doing any more good; or being any farther ſerviceable in his Generation. There is no praiſing or praying in the <hi>Grave,</hi> or any remembrance of God or Man. As the Tree falls by Death, it will lye till Judgment, without bringing forth any fruit at all. Whilſt Man is in the Land of the Living, he is capable of doing ſome good; or being uſeful in that place and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion wherein God hath ſet him. But when Death cuts him off; his day of opportunity is at an end, and the night is come up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, in which he cannot work, nor do any more as he hath done. And therefore there is juſt cauſe of Mourning and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting at his Deceaſe. Thus the Widows of <hi>Joppa</hi> Bewailed the Death of <hi>Tabitha, a Woman full of good Works, and Alms-deeds,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:37946:13"/>which ſhe had done,</hi> Acts 9. ver. 39. <hi>Then</hi> Peter <hi>aroſe and went with them; when he was come, they brought him into the upper Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; and all the Widows ſtood by him Weeping, and ſhewing the Coats and Garments which</hi> Dorcas <hi>made while ſhe was with them.</hi> By which they commended her Charity, and bitterly Bewailed her fatal <hi>Exit.</hi> The thoughts of parting with ſuch a Woman, who was ſo charitable, ſo uſeful; even broke their Hearts with Sorrow, and diſſolved their Eyes with Tears. They brought the <hi>Garments</hi> to view (which ſhe had made to cloath the Backs of the Naked with) and ſet them before <hi>Peter,</hi> and the reſt that accompanied him, to juſtify the ground of their <hi>Mourning;</hi> or rather, to heighten the Paſſion of their <hi>Sorrow,</hi> from this ſadning conſideration, that ſhe was ever uncapable of making any more; that the Poor were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver like to be the better for her again; They could not but <hi>Mourn,</hi> that ſhe was ſo ſoon taken off from proſecuting the many good pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects ſhe had in her Head arid Heart, of being uſeful to the Poor, and them that were in Diſtreſs. Ah, Sirs! when we ſee a Man going to his <hi>Grave,</hi> we may ſadly cry out, <hi>He will never, he can never do any more good;</hi> His opportunity of glorifying his Creator, or of ſerving his fellow-Creature, is paſt and gone, and will never return again. It is impoſſible he ſhould be any farther ſerviceable in <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>Common-Wealth.</hi> And ſurely this ſhould enforce a <hi>Mourning</hi> from all, who take delight in, or are capable of receiving Comfort from the doing good of others. But it may be, you will ſay, there are many Men that do no good at all while they Live, but a great deal of harm; who are ſo far from being uſeful, that they are wholly unprofitable; yea, very prejudicial to God's ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and Man's welfare in their Generation; That are a <hi>Plague</hi> to the place where their abode is, and a <hi>Curſe</hi> to all, whoſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happineſs it is to be near them. Now, ſhould we Mourn for them, ſhould we Grieve when they are taken out of the World; ſhould we go as <hi>Mourners about the Streets,</hi> when ſuch barren Trees are cut down, and carried to their <hi>Long Home?</hi> Yes, verily, we ſhould; becauſe, while a wicked Man is alive, there is hope, or at leaſt, a poſſibility of his Recovery from his wicked State; of his being waſhed and ſanctified in the Name of the Lord Jeſus, and by the Spirit of our God. But when he dyes, there is no poſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of his reclaiming, or being renewed to Repentance—for there is no work, no device, no invention (and I may add, no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation)
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:37946:14"/>in the <hi>Grave,</hi> whither we are going.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> For that when a Man <hi>Dyes,</hi> and goes to his <hi>Long Home,</hi> we ſhall never ſee him more: he vaniſhes (as it were) out of our ſight, and we are never more to behold him, or caſt our Eyes upon him. He is both actively and paſſively in an inviſible ſtate. So <hi>Job</hi> Mournfully ſpeaks of himſelf, <hi>chap.</hi> 7. <hi>ver.</hi> 7, 8. <hi>Oh remember that my Life is wind, my Eyes ſhall no more ſee good. The Eye of him that hath ſeen me, ſhall ſee me no more; thy Eyes are upon me, and I am not.</hi> What more cutting Expreſſion, what more ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Inculcation, what more provoking Incitation to <hi>Mourning,</hi> can there be, than the Sence of this; that we ſhall behold the Face of our beloved Friend (after his departure from us) no more! Were Man to Return, though after never ſo many Years abſence from his home, or continuance in the <hi>Grave:</hi> Were he to viſit his habitation again, and become the objective delight of his poor <hi>Mourning</hi> Friends and Relations, it might be ſome al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leviation to their Grief, when he takes his journey to his <hi>Long Home.</hi> But Oh! What a prick to the Heart, what a ſtab to the Soul, what a deadning to the Spirits, what an inundation of Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row (like the opening of <hi>Pandora</hi>'s Box) is this lamentable Thought to an ingenious Man, that he muſt never, never, never more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the Face of this or that Relation in this Region of Mortality; nor have any converſe with him on this ſide the Bank of Eternity! What Husband can think ſo of his Wife, and not melt? what Wife can have ſuch a thought of her Husband, and not faint? what Parent can conſider this, with reſpect to his Child, and not mourn? what Child can reflect upon the impoſſibility of ever ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Father or Mother more, and not be overwhelmed with grief? In a word, What Friend or Relation can ponder on ſuch an eternal Farewel, as is then given, and not be diſſolved into Tears; yea, and not to Mourning like the Mourning of <hi>Hada-drimmon,</hi> when Cloyſtered up in <hi>Megiddo</hi>'s Vale? It is the opinion of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, That the chiefeſt of the Saints happineſs, conſiſts in Viſion, or in the uſe of the viſive faculty, which will then be enlarged, and made glorious to perfection; for they ſhall ſee the Face of God in Righteouſneſs, and be ſatisfied with his likeneſs; they ſhall be for ever with open Face, beholding (as in a Glaſs) the Glory of the Lord, and be changed into the ſame Image, from Glory to Glory, even as by the Spirit of the Lord. Sure I am, the Saints greateſt
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:37946:14"/>comfort in this World, conſiſts in Viſion, or beholding God's Image in his People; and that not only the work of his Power in their comely Features, but the work of his Grace in the divine Characters of Wiſdom, engraven in their Souls, and immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reflected upon in all their Actions. Therefore it cannot but cauſe Mourning, when ſuch delightful Objects are removed out of ſight, and never more to be beheld.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly, <hi>Modifically;</hi>
               </hi> There is a modifick Obligation upon the Living, to <hi>Mourn</hi> for the Dead; in reſpect of the manner of Mens Dying, or the circumſtances they are under, in that great Hour.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> For that Sickneſs is the Prologue of it; the Paleneſs of Death, is generally uſhered in with the Pains and Sorrows of Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Thus it was with the Child of the great <hi>Shunamite,</hi> that had ſo courteouſly entertained <hi>Eliſha,</hi> and built a Chamber for him; Furniſhing it with thoſe Utenſils, which ſhe knew were moſt acceptable to a contemplative Man: In requital of which kindneſs, he promiſed her from God, a Child; and a Child ſhe had, but it Dyed; but before it Dyed, it fell Sick, and was tormented with Pains. So we are told, 2 <hi>King. chap.</hi> 4. <hi>ver.</hi> 18, 19. <hi>And when the Child was grown, it fell on a day that he went out to his Father, to the Reapers: And he ſaid unto his Father, my Head, my head; and he ſaid to a Lad, carry him to his Mother. And when he had taken him, and brought him to his Mother, he ſate on her Knees till Noon, and then Dyed.</hi> His Head firſt Aked, before his Breath Departed. And this is the uſual way of Men's Dying; firſt to complain of ſome Diſeaſe in their Bodies, before there is a ſeparation between that, and their Souls: One crys out of his Head, another of his Bowels; one is Sore-pained, another is Heart-ſick upon his taking his leave of the World. And as the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaks of the laſt times, <hi>The Sun ſhall be turned into Darkneſs, and the Moon into Blood, before the great and notable Day of the Lord comes.</hi> So it is moſt true in this caſe; Health ſhall be turned into Sickneſs, Strength into Weakneſs, Pleaſure into Pain, Delight into Sadneſs, before the great and notable Day of Death comes. Which indeed (in it ſelf conſidered, abſtracted from the hopes of a future Being) is a day of Wrath; a day of Trouble and Diſtreſs, a day of Waſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Deſolation; a day of Darkneſs and Gloomyneſs; a day of Clouds and thick Darkneſs; a day of the Trumpet, and Alarum
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:37946:15"/>againſt the ſenced Cities, and againſt the high Tower. Now who can behold a Friend in any pain, or under the power of any Diſtemper upon a ſick Bed, and not Grieve at it? What Object calls more for Pity and Commiſeration, yea for Grief and Lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, than a pained Heart-ſick-man, who cannot help himſelf, or receive Eaſe from any Application; eſpecially of that pain that precedes his Diſſolution; for</p>
            <q>Contra vim mortis non eſt medicamen in hortis.</q>
            <p>And as Diſtempers are coroding and tormenting in their Natures, ſo they are Multitudinous in their number. There are innumerable Diſeaſes that go before Death, that are as purſivants in the ſame Livery, warning the Sons of Men to be ready at Deaths approach according to the Poet,</p>
            <q>Mille modis lethi miſeros mors una fatigat.</q>
            <p>And as another well expreſſeth it,</p>
            <q>Mille modis Morimur miſeri ſed Naſcimur uno.</q>
            <p>There is but one way of our coming into the World; but a Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, of our going out. 'Twas a <hi>Curſe</hi> upon Man after his <hi>Fall,</hi> that he ſhould live by the <hi>Sweat of his Brow,</hi> and the ſame Curſe hath entailed this miſery upon him, that he muſt Dye in the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh of his Soul.</hi> As he Lives in <hi>Sweat,</hi> ſo he Dyes in <hi>Pain;</hi> and this Pain cannot but enforce <hi>Mourning</hi> from all tender-hearted Spec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tators that are about him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> For that a Dying-man, is really himſelf a Mourning-man. When Man is going to his <hi>Long Home,</hi> his Soul is clad with <hi>Cypreſs;</hi> his Spirits are drooping, and in a ſorrowful trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling poſture, he is waiting the finiſhing of Deaths laſt ſtroke: He lies groaning, and pitifully crying out on his ſick-bed; and with rowling-eyes, lifted-up hands, and panting breaſts; he ſighs, he ſobs, he dyes. And from this condition, good Men are no more exempted, than wicked, at their deaths; nay, we find the beſt of Men, even buried in Sorrow, in the day of his humiliation, when he was going to his Death, <hi>Matth.</hi> 26. <hi>ver.</hi> 38. <hi>Then ſaith he unto them, my Soul is exceeding Sorrowful, even unto Death, tarry ye here, and watch with me.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. The word ſignifies, <hi>Fear on every ſide.</hi> The faculties of his Soul were (as it were) beſet, and beſieged with Grief: Sorrow went round about him. Indeed, <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> would not own, that a Man of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit could be capable of ſuch a Sorrow; but 'twas his ignorance in
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:37946:15"/>the things of God, which made him think ſo: And our Saviour's ſorrowful poſture, is a ſufficient confutation of that Notion. Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily Sirs, when the terrors of Death (notwithſtanding the Sting of it is taken away) takes hold upon the moſt Heroick-ſpirited; yea, upon the moſt gracious qualified among the Sons of Men, it makes him preſently hang his Harp upon the Willow-tree, and hide his Face within the drawn Curtains; converting his Songs into Sighs, his Laughing into Mourning; and all his Rejoycing into heavy Groans; Emblematically be ſpeaking to all that are round about him, with a ſhaking head, and ghaſtly look, what <hi>Job</hi> did ſo paſſionately—<hi>Have pity upon me, Oh ye my Friends, have pity upon me; for the Hand of God</hi> (yea, the hand of Death) <hi>hath touched mt.</hi> Help, help! O Wife! O Children! What ſhall I do; my Spirits are fainting, my Breath is going, my Soul is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting, and I muſt leave you all! And then turning, ſighs and ſobs to that ſorrowful Note of <hi>Jobs, Oh that I were as in Months paſt, as in the day when God preſerved me: When his Candle ſhined up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my Head; and when by his Light I walked through Darkneſs: as I was in the dayes of my Youth, when the Secret of God was upon my Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle.</hi> Thus poor Man concludes the Tragick-Scene of his trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome Life, inbreathing out ſuch doleful Epicediums. He came into the World, <hi>Crying,</hi> and he goes out, <hi>Sighing.</hi> He Crys the firſt thing he does, after he is Born, and he Sobs the laſt thing he does, before he Dyes. Now what Heart can be ſo obdurate, to behold Man expiring in the midſt of his Sigh, and not ſay, as <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> ſaid of <hi>Lazarus—Lord let its go, that we may Dye with him: So let me go and Sob with him, and bear him company in the bitter Ago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny he is now in.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> For the great change Death makes in the perſon De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed; of an active lively Man, he is become a dead lump of Clay; ſo changed, and wholly altered in the Phyſiognomy, and outward appearance of the Body: that we may ſay with the Poet,</p>
            <q>Qui color albus erat nunc eſt contrarius albo:</q>
            <p>The Man that a day or two ago, lookt ſo freſh and fair, Oh how pale, how wan, how ghaſtly, how affrightning does he look now! The Man that was ſo pleaſant, ſo every way deſirable in his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation a little while ago; how loathſome and deteſtable does he appear now; That it makes his deareſt Relations ſay of him, as <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaid of <hi>Sarah, Gen.</hi> 23. <hi>ver.</hi> 4. <hi>I am a ſtranger
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:37946:16"/>and a ſojourner with you, give me a poſſeſſion of a Burying place with you, that I may Bury my Dead out of my ſight.</hi> Sad was the Change death made in <hi>Sarah,</hi> which enforced this ſo ſeeming unnatural Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in <hi>Abraham,</hi> to put her out of his ſight. He could no longer look upon her, as his delightful Wife to ſleep in his Boſom; but as a rotten piece of Fleſh, that muſt be removed away. Man in his Coffin, is like a growing flower; how ſplendidly does it look, how fragrantly does it ſmell, whilſt upon the ſtalk; but no ſooner cropt, but it preſently fades, and in a few hours is trodden under foot, as dirt. So that we may ſay of him, as the Nations ſaid of the King of <hi>Babylon—His Pomp is brought down to the</hi> Grave, <hi>and the noiſe of his Viols; the Worm is ſpread under him, and the Worms cover him:</hi> Oh! Sirs, All Man's Pomp, his Beauty, his Glory is then withered away. And as it was ſaid of our Redeemer (in his ſtate of humiliation) <hi>There is no from or comelineſs to look upon him, nor no beauty in him, that we ſhould deſire him.</hi> His Body is then a contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible, deſpicable, abominable thing: Hence the Apoſtle makes uſe of theſe expreſſions of meanneſs, and contemptibleneſs, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning man's going to his <hi>Long Home;</hi> elegantly ſhewing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, what his Body (under thoſe circumſtances) is; <hi>It is ſown in corruption</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in a ſtate of filthineſs and contamination: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, <hi>It is ſown in diſhonor</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in a ſtate of ignominy and contempt: Again, <hi>It is ſown in weakneſs,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in a ſtate of inability to withſtand the Power of Death. Once more, <hi>It is ſown a natural Body,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, A Body ſubjected to all the miſeries ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaining to, and entailed upon Apoſtate Nature. From all this, we may gather the proper deſcription of the Body, when it is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for, and carrying to the <hi>Grave.</hi> It is a filthy polluted, a baſe ignominious, a frail impotent, a rotting periſhing Body. This is the outward ſtate of every man, when Death has mow'd him down. And therefore we ſhould <hi>Mourn</hi> at ſo great and ſudden a Change: Though I confeſs our <hi>Mourning</hi> ſhould be in hope, with reſpect to the departure of the Godly: For though their Bodys be <hi>Sown in corruption,</hi> they will be <hi>Raiſed in incorruption;</hi> though <hi>Sown in diſhonor,</hi> they will be <hi>Raiſed in glory;</hi> though <hi>Sown in weakneſs,</hi> they will be <hi>Raiſed in Power;</hi> though <hi>Sown natural,</hi> they will be <hi>Raiſed ſpiritual Bodys.</hi> For their corruptible muſt put on incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, and their mortal muſt put on immortality; and then Death it ſelf ſhall be ſwallowed up in Victory. But the preſent
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:37946:16"/>change in their Bodies by Death, calls for a due Mourning from their Survivors.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> For the great change and alteration Death makes in the place of the Deceaſed; the great Vacuum there is, when Man is removed, and carried away to his <hi>Long Home:</hi> Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning which, <hi>Job</hi> excellently ſpeaks, <hi>chap.</hi> 7. <hi>v.</hi> 9, 10, 11. <hi>As the cloud is conſumed, and vaniſheth away: ſo he that goeth down to the</hi> Grave, <hi>ſhall come up no more. He ſhall return no more to his houſe, neither ſhall his place know him any more. Therefore I will not refrain my Mouth, I will ſpeak in the anguiſh of my Spirit, I will complain in the bitterneſs of my Soul.</hi> Oh! It is very ſad to conſider what a great change one ſtroke of Death may make. A Wife Husbandleſs, poor Children Fatherleſs, Servants Maſterleſs, and many Friends Comfortleſs: And ſo great is the alteration in the Family, that the whole Houſe reſents it; and ſeems ſilently to <hi>Mourn</hi> for it. There is (as it were) a Face of ſadneſs in every place he was wont to be conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant in: Look in his Parlour, where he uſed to ſit with his Wife, and Children about him, and there is nothing but a profound ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence; his voice is not to be heard: Look at his Table, where he uſed to ſit with chearfulneſs, eating his Bread with joy among his Relations, and the dull demeaner, and ſorrowful poſture of all the aſſeſſors, do plainly, yet dolefully ſpeak; Behold, he is not here: Look in his Shop, where he uſed to be about his occaſions; and the diſorder and confuſion there, proclaims aloud his being gone, and not to be heard of: In a word, Look in every place where he us'd to be, and you will find one mourning circumſtance or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, a legible Hiſtorian of his departure, and being no more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them. So that, if you ſeek him, you will not find him; if you ask for him, you will hear no news. Now ſurely, methinks, the very miſs of a Man in his Family, the want of him in his place, the great change immediately following his Departure in all his Affairs and Concerns, ſhould be cauſe enough to enforce a <hi>Mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> from his Survivors, if there were no other conſideration.</p>
            <p>Thus I have ſhown you in what reſpects there is a <hi>Mourning</hi> due from the Surviving, to the Deceaſed; and why we ought to be <hi>Mourners</hi> in the <hi>Street,</hi> when we ſee a Man going to his <hi>Long Home;</hi> even from a Natural, Relative, Moral, Modifical conſideration, obliging us thereunto.</p>
            <p>I now paſs from the Doctrinal, to the Applicatory part of this
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:37946:17"/>ſad and ſolemn Truth: And the only uſe I ſhall make of it, ſhall be a word of Exhortation, to put this Duty in practiſe, now in the day and ſeaſon thereof. Never was an occaſion more doleful, than that which has brought us hither this day: Never was a Text more ſuitable than this, which is now to be applyed to the Occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. So that, what Application is to be made, will be, <hi>Verbum diei in die ſuo, A word of day in its proper day.</hi> Look Sirs, in yon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Coffin lies a Man known unto us, and beloved by us, ready to go (when we ſhall put our hands to carry him) to his <hi>Long Home.</hi> Oh! ſhould not we this day be as <hi>Mourners in the Street.</hi> Oh! that we could, our ſelves, as really evidence the Truth of the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter part of the words, in being <hi>Mourners;</hi> as our deceaſed Brother before us, has done of the former part, in going to his <hi>Long Home.</hi> Verily Sirs, This is the day, the very day, in which the Lord God of Hoſts, calls to <hi>Weeping,</hi> and to <hi>Mourning,</hi> to <hi>Baldneſs,</hi> and to <hi>Girding with Sack-cloath.</hi> And therefore, I ſhall make uſe of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> words, for the preſſing this Exhortation, <hi>James</hi> 4. <hi>ver.</hi> 9. <hi>Be Afflicted, ana Mourn, and Weep; let your Laughter be turned, to Mourning, and your Joy to Heavineſs.</hi> Not a word here but has its Emphaſis, and deſervies a ſpecial Notation <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: Be touched with a ſenſe of miſery, and that in your Hearts, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Mourn</hi> in an exceeding great meaſure, expreſſed in ſome outward, overt-Act, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Weep from a broken and tender Heath This Weeping is Natures priviledge, forbiddon by none; as the Poet intimates,</p>
            <q>Quis matrem niſi mentis inops in funore nati flere vet at.</q>
            <p>Again, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Let you Laughter, or loud Acclamations of Mirth and Jollity, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, be turned into Mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or into a Funeral Elegy or Lamentation. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Your Joy, or the greateſt Delight and Contentment, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, into Heavineſs, or into a Sorrow, that dejects the Countenance, and makes Men look down-ward upon the Earth. Now Sirs, put all this together, &amp; that is it which I would preſs you to this day. Oh! Be ſo Afflicted, as to be touched with a ſence of this awful diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of divine Providence, in viſiting us ſo ſorely in this the day of his Anger. And then Mourn in a viſible real manner. And Weep till your Hearts are even broken with Sorrow. Let your Laughter or outward expreſſions of Mirth, be turned into Mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or grievous burſting forth into Tears. And let your Joy,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:37946:17"/>or any thing of delight, be turned into Heavineſs; or into a real dejectedneſs, or calling down: And the reaſon is very obvious; this Coffin herd before us, does juſtly call for it, as containing one, who was lately the Object of our Love and Eſteem; but now the deſerved Subject of our Sighs and Tears. It is not my principle, nor uſual practiſe, to ſpeak much on ſuch occaſions of the Perſon deceaſed. The cuſtom of ſome Predicants, is rather to be bewailed, than imitated, who are inconſiderately Studious to hoiſe up the Names of thoſe, who they would ſtutter as high as Heaven, when perhaps at the ſame time, their Souls are roaring in the hotteſt Hell. 'Tis alſo of dangerous conſequence to the Auditors. Funeral Encomiaſticks of the Dead, prove often confections of poyſon to the Living. People may well grow careleſs of their Lives, when cuſtom layes an obligation upon the Preacher, to Hackney them to Heaven in his Sermon, when they Dye. But here is ſomething ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary in this Funeral, that may be my Apology, for ſpeaking ſomething concerning him, who is going to his <hi>Long Home</hi> this day. He Dying here in a ſtrange Country, far from his Relations, where none of his Fathers ever were; and that befalling him, which the Poet accounting a great miſery,</p>
            <q>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>:</q>
            <p>'Tis true, he was not drowned, and ſo did not Dye in the Waters in that ſence; but he Dyed upon the Waters, and is now to be Buried in the Waters: And therefore I think it but highly juſt, to ſtrew ſome deſerved Flowers on his Herſe, that we may all carry home the Fragrancy of his <hi>Name</hi> in our Memories, ſince we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not carry home his <hi>Body</hi> to his dear Mourning Relations. Beſides, I look upon my ſelf as obliged to ſpeak, becauſe I knew more of him, than any, I believe, in the World, did. He was pleaſed to make my Breaſt die Repoſitory, where he locked the very Secrets of his Soul: Never two were more intimate; we were pleaſant to each other in our Lives: Oh! that in our Deaths we had not been divided. However, my love to him, and intimacy with him, ſhall not trappan me into any thing of Flattery, which I ever abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. And hence I will not inſiſt upon what I wiſh I could do more <hi>(viz)</hi> his exemplarineſs in Piety; Although I am more than confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, the <hi>Root of the matter</hi> was in him. I know his unavoidable Aſſociation with all ſorts of Company betrayed him to ſome tinctures of vanity, which himſelf was ſenſible of, and moſt deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:37946:18"/>bewailed upon his dying Bed. But for an example of Morali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, a modle of Civility, a platform of all Humanity; I dare pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to preſent you with as exact an one, as has been ſeen in this Latter-Age. I remember what the Orator ſayes; <hi>Frigida lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datio mera vituperatio.</hi> A cold kind of praiſing, is no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than a diſpraiſing. Hence, what I ſhall ſay, ſhall be in the words of Truth, Sobriety , and (I think) juſtifiable Fervency. I will begin with his Extraction. His Birth was truly honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable; for he was Born of the race of the Firſt-born, being immediately deſcended from the Loyns of the Prophets, and ſuch (as in their day) were Stars of the firſt Magnitude, enrowled in the Catalogue of thoſe Worthyes, of whom the World was not worthy. His Grand-Father, Mr. <hi>Richard Bernard</hi> of <hi>Batcomb,</hi> a moſt famous elabourate Divine, whoſe Name is as Oyntment poured forth; whoſe Works praiſe him in the Gate, and whoſe Memory will never dye, ſo long as Religion lives in <hi>England.</hi> His Father alſo an able eminent Miniſter, the Husband of one Wife, by whom he had (I think) One and Twenty Children, of whom this, our deceaſed Friend, was the youngeſt: So that he was their <hi>Benjamin,</hi> the Staff of their Old Age; they were careful of his Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and infuſed thoſe great principles of Truth into his Infant-years; the ſavor of which, he retained to the laſt; ſo true is that,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quo Yemel eſt imbuta recens ſervabit odorem Teſta Diu:</hi> Or, as <hi>Solomon</hi> Engliſhes it, <hi>Train up a Child in the way wherein he ſhould walk, and when he is old, he will not depart from it:</hi> He was <hi>Filius Fidelium &amp; Precum; A Child of the Covenant, and a Child of Prayers.</hi> There was a great ſtock of Prayers laid up for him; and I am perſwaded they were not loſt. After he had paſt his impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berous days under his Parents Wings in the Country; he was ſent up to <hi>London</hi> to his Brother, Mr. <hi>John Bernard,</hi> a pious holy Man, in great eſteem amongſt the Godly; who was more than a Brother, yea a Father to him (as I have often heard him acknowledge, with a great ſence of Gratitude) he took great care about diſpoſing of him, in order to his future Settlement. At length he placed him with an honeſt Maſter, whom he faithfully and truly Served: I have heard his Maſter ſay this of him, He never had ſuch a Servant. His Calling obliged him to uſe the Seas, which he was as unfit for, as the Sea was unworthy of him. He had a reach at higher things,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:37946:18"/>and his Heroick Spirit hardly brooked the Converſation genuine to this Element; he had an exceeding good Natural Wit, a Ripe Invention, a Quick Fancy, a Logical Head, a Strong Memory; and (as a Crown to all) a Great Judgment: He was an univerſal accompliſht Man, able to carry himſelf Aptly, and to ſpeak Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruouſly in all Companys, from the King's Court, to the Beggars Cottage. He was endued with that Humility and Modeſty, which very well became his Young years; and yet with that Depth and Judgment, that was a great deal above his Years. He was unſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able after Knowledge, eſpecially in the beſt things. He would often bring me ſome of the hardeſt Scriptures to explain, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſome of the abſtruceſt Points in Divinity, to be reſolved. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed he had Notions of a very high Birth, and Conceptions far above one under his Circumſtances: Inſomuch, that I have often admired him, and ſaid of him, as the Multitude, of our Saviour, <hi>From whence hath this Man this Wiſdom?</hi> He was a conſtant hearer of the Word, and a great Honourer of thoſe that delivered it: He dearly Lov'd a Learned Miniſtry, and by ſuch was he Beloved. Several eminent Divines in <hi>London</hi> had an high Reſpect for him. The truth is, I knew not any (whoſe Judgments was worth a minding) that were acquainted with him, but very deeply affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him, and eſteemed him, as one of a more than ordinary Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity. He greatly delighted in reading good Books, eſpecially Dr. <hi>Bates, Of the Exiſtence of God; His Harmony of the Divine Attributes:</hi> and Mr. <hi>Baxters Directory:</hi> which he mightily pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, and would often ſay, he looked upon it as the next Book to the Bible. In his Match, he preferred Virtue before Money; contrary to the Genius of this corrupt Age. He adviſed with me, and indeed gave himſelf up wholly to me, to chooſe a Wife for him. In order to which, I brought him acquainted with an honeſt Religious Family, to which he was ſoon Related, by eſpouſing a Wife, that Heaven in Mercy, had every way prepared an Help meet for him: In whom he took great Delight; as alſo in the Piety, and Ingenuity of her Relations; with whoſe Society he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed himſelf a great deal of Comfort and Satisfaction, at his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn from this Voyage: But poor Gentleman, he is now gone, Death has fruſtrated all his Expectations of that kind. <hi>Labitur Savo Rapiente Fato</hi> (to uſe <hi>Senecas</hi> words) he is taken away by the over-ruling Powers above; never to be among his poor Relations,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:37946:19"/>or to be ſeen by them any more for ever. He had an admirable mixture and mediocrity in the whole of his Deportment; he was Facetious, and yet Solid; Affable, and yet Reſerved; Courteous to all, and yet Familiar with very few: He was a moſt Juſt Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Man in all his Dealings: I never knew him guilty of the leaſt dirty or diſingenuous Action: He was a faithful and true Friend: <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſque ad aras.</hi> I found him ſo in my three years acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with him, and conſtant abode with him, both at Sea, and a Shoar. And I have reaſon to know him; for in all that time, we were very rarely a whole day aſunder. The truth is, no Change but this of Death could ever have parted us in this World. I Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienced ſuch a Tranſcendency, Peculiarity, Conſtancy in his Friendſhip, that I deſpair of ever meeting with ſuch another Friend here below. He was a Credit to his Friends, an Honour to his Family; and the Glory of all his Relations. To Conclude, I do with all imaginable ſeriouſneſs, ſolemnly profeſs (without the leaſt Flattery, or ſiniſter Reſpects) according to my beſt knowledge of him (which was as great as was poſſible for one Man to have of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother) upon a long, and critical obſerving the whole Courſe of his Life (the greateſt Secrets of which, were not hid from me). He was the moſt Cordate, Innocent, Faithful, Ingenious, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very way Obliging Man, that (in all my Travels through the World, which have been much, or in my Converſe with Men of all ſorts, which has been great) I ever ſaw, or was acquainted with. He wanted no Quality of a Man to make him Amiable, nor no Property of a Friend to make him Deſirable. For my part, I may truly take up the Lamentation of <hi>David</hi> over <hi>Jonathan,</hi> 2 Sam. 1. <hi>ver.</hi> 26. <hi>I am diſtreſſed for thee my Brother</hi> Richard, <hi>very pleaſant haſt thou been unto me; thy Love to me was wonderful, paſſing the Love of Women.</hi> And therefore I cannot but <hi>Mourn</hi> my ſelf, and invite you to <hi>Mourn</hi> with me: And though my Loſs is more particular, more peculiar than any of yours; yet there is never an one here, but has a Loſs, a great Loſs in this Worthy Man; and ought deeply to lay it to Heart, and manifeſt the ſence of it, by a due and regular <hi>Mourning.</hi> And that I may Methodically, and Gradu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally lead you into the Valley of <hi>Baca;</hi> Conſider I beſeech you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> We have Loſt a Man—one of our Society is gone, and ſo our number is leſſened. Now, if the Loſs of a Man ought to be taken notice of in a Nation, or in a City, when there are Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:37946:19"/>ſtill left, how much more conſiderable is ſuch a Loſs to us, who have ſo few in this our Wooden World. Beſides, this is not the firſt (though indeed the greateſt) Loſs we have had of this kind. Death has been no ſtranger to us, from the beginning of the Voyage. You know, before we were clear from <hi>Graves-End</hi> (a very ſutable name, for it is ſo to many a parting Friend) Death ſate threatning of us in a Terrible manner upon the <hi>Miſon-Maſt,</hi> from whence he ſent a Man (to the endangering of his own Life) on his diſmal Errand, to Summon a poor Boy to his <hi>Long Home,</hi> who out-lived not two days, the Blow he received by the others Fall upon him. And by that time we were got to the <hi>Downs,</hi> Death was upon the <hi>Catharpins;</hi> from whence, in the twinkling of an Eye, he tumbled one of our Men dead upon the Deck. And he has been ſince rainging up and down the Ship, every now and then taking one away from us, which ought to be laid to Heart by us. But behold, now he is come up to the <hi>Quarter-Deck,</hi> and has ſmitten one of our chiefeſt and choiſeſt Men with his fatal Dart. Oh! ſhould not we then be affected with ſuch a dreadful Stroke as this. I am ſure in the Preachers Opinion we ſhould, and that not only in the Text, but elſe-where, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7. <hi>ver.</hi> 2. <hi>It is better to go to the Houſe of Mourning, than to the Houſe of Feaſting; for that is the End of all Men, and the Living will lay it to Heart.</hi> That is, the Living ought to lay it to Heart, and ſo Mourn, and be Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled at it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Conſider, we have Loſt a Friend, a true Friend, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſtricteſt Notions of Friendſhip, which is a Jewel not common, nor of little value now a days: We may now, more than ever, take up that old Complaint,</p>
            <q>
               <l>Illud amicitiae Quondam venerabile nomen,</l>
               <l>Proſtat &amp; in Queſtu pro meritrice ſolet.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Friendſhip is now expoſed to Sale, and become a painted Strum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, to ſerve the turns a little while of thoſe that will give moſt Mony for her. But our Deceaſed Brother, was one of a Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, a Friend indeed: His Friendſhip was real and pure, without any mixture of droſſy ſelf-ends: So that what Chriſt ſaid to his Diſciples, <hi>John</hi> 11. <hi>ver.</hi> 11. <hi>Theſe things ſaid he, and after that, he ſaith unto them, Our Friend</hi> Lazarus <hi>ſleepeth, but I go that I may awake him out of ſleep.</hi> We may all of us apply to him in the Coffin, now before us, our Friend <hi>Richard</hi> ſleepth, he is laid down up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:37946:20"/>on his everlaſting Pillar, never to be awakned till the day of the Reſurrection. He Lov'd us all with a tender Love, and ſerv'd us all with a faithful Care. Oh! how ready, and willing was he to do good to the meaneſt amongſt us. How did he pity, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſerate any poor Man in Pain or Diſtreſs. How have I ſeen him Weep when he could not Cure. And how Charitable was he to his poor Patients; never ſparing, but plentifully ſpending of his own, to make things good and comfortable for them: And he would often tell me, he could not but in Conſcience do it. And for the truth of this, I do, and can appeal to moſt of you that hear me this day; you know it as well as I: Who then can deny him this Golden Title of a Friend? And he gave ſufficient proofs of his Friendſhip in the very laſt act of his Life, when he deſired me to ſend for the Officers. Oh! with what uncommon Marks of Affection, with what Tranſport of Paſſion, with what Heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melting Compellations did he take his Dying Farewel of us, even then, when his Cheeks were Pale, when his Lips were Cold, when his Eyes were ready to be cloſed. Ah! can we reflect upon the Living Marks of his Friendſhip, and the Dying Tokens of his Love, and not be as <hi>Mourners</hi> about his Hearſe, now he is going to his <hi>Long Home.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Conſider we have Loſt a Skilful Man, one that was a perfect Maſter of his Profeſſion; a compleat Artiſt in every thing that belonged thereunto. He was well Read, and Studyed in the beſt Phyſical Authors; the Sence of all which, in any difficult point, he had <hi>ad unguem:</hi> Beſides, his great Experience, and Practice of all Sorts, which made him every way fit to undertake ſo great a Charge as he had upon him. I heard an Eminent and Learned Phyſitian in <hi>London,</hi> ſay of him, That conſidering his Years and Circumſtances, he never diſcourſed with his fellow, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to give ſo rational an Account of the Nature of any Diſtemper, and to preſcribe ſuch proper Applications for the Expelling it. He was very Skilful in Timing all that he did to his Patients: whatever he did, was in the proper day and ſeaſon thereof, well knowing that to be a great truth, which the Poet tells us,</p>
            <q>
               <l>In recto medecina valent data Tempore proſunt,</l>
               <l>Et data non apto Tempore vina nocent.</l>
            </q>
            <p>The truth is, he was Skilful in every thing that conduced to his Patients Good. So that, great is our Loſs in this reſpect. Indeed,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:37946:20"/>the whole of that Judgment is come upon us, which God threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his antient People with, in the days of old, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 3. <hi>ver.</hi> 1, 2, 3. <hi>For behold, the Lord, the</hi> Lord <hi>of Hoſts doth take away from</hi> Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, <hi>and from</hi> Judah, <hi>the ſtay and the ſtaff, the whale ſtay of Bread, and the whole ſtaff of Water: The Mighty Man, and the Man of War; the Judge, and the Prophet, and the Prudent, and the Antient<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The Captain of Fifty, and the Honourable Man, and the Counſellor, and the Cunning Artificer, and the Eloquent Orator.</hi> Ah! verily our <hi>ſtay</hi> and our <hi>ſtaff</hi> is gone; He that was the <hi>ſtay</hi> of our Strength, and the <hi>ſtaff</hi> of our Lives: He that was a <hi>cunning artificer,,</hi> and a <hi>skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Operator</hi> in the concerns of our Bodies, is now taken away; therefore we ought to be <hi>Mourners about his Hearſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Conſider, we have Loſt an Uſeful Man; yea, a Man of the greateſt Uſe amongſt us. The variety of Diſtempers Men are afflicted with, and ſubject to, in theſe Hot Climates, do ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently infer the Uſefulneſs; yea, the Neceſſity of an able Phyſitian. I know you look upon your Miniſter as a needleſs Perſon, becauſe you are unſenſible of the worth of your Souls; if he had gone, you would not have accounted it any great loſs: Ah! but now Sirs, God knew how to take that Mercy from you, which you are moſt ſenſible of the worth and uſe of; He knew where to prick the Vein that will moſt Bleed; and therefore he has taken away the Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian of your Bodies, whom you may moſt dearly miſs, before you go home. And ſurely this beſpeaks your <hi>Mourning</hi> in a grievous and bitter manner, for this ſo ſharp a Stroke: What <hi>Paul</hi> told the <hi>Coloſſians,</hi> chap. 4 ver. 14. <hi>Luke the beloved Phyſician, and</hi> Demas <hi>greet you:</hi> May be truly applyed to him, who was indeed a beloved Phyſician; and he deſerved no other, for his diligent care and pains towards the meaneſt Patient. He was ſeldome ſent for to any ſick Perſon, being ſo forward of himſelf to go, as ſoon as he heard of it. Moſt Applications he made uſe of, went through his own hands, though the Diſeaſe was never ſo loathſome, or the Perſon never ſo mean. How then may I beſpeak your <hi>Mourning o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver his Hearſe</hi> this day, us <hi>David</hi> did the <hi>Mourning</hi> of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> over <hi>Saul: Ye Daughters of</hi> Iſrael <hi>weep over</hi> Saul, <hi>who cloathed you in Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let, and ether delights; who put on ornaments of Gold on your Apparel:</hi> So, <hi>O ye Seamen and Officers of this Ship,</hi> Weep over this Painful, Diligent, Affectionate Phyſitian, who refreſhed you with Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dials, and other delights: Who was day and night ſerviceable to
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:37946:21"/>you, and Dyed in that ſervice amongſt you. He is now gone to his <hi>Long Home,</hi> who retrieved many of us, when we were almoſt there. He helped us, but we could not help him. Ah! how can we think of parting with ſuch an Uſeful, Faithful, Affectionate Friend, and not <hi>Mourn.</hi> How can we think of throwing him (who was the very delight of our Souls) Over-board into the wide Ocean, to be made a Prey to the devouring Fiſhes, and not break forth into doleful Crys and Lamentations.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee the cauſe we have to <hi>Mourn,</hi> from the Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the greatneſs of our preſent Loſs: But the many aggrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting circumſtances of this Loſs, do yet call for our <hi>Farther Mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> and the ſcruing up our <hi>Sorrow</hi> one Peg higher. Hence conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> He is taken away before our Voyage is done: It would have been a very conſiderable Loſs, if he had Lived with us to <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and then have been removed by Death: It would then have called for <hi>Mourning</hi> at our hands. I, but it would not have been ſo diſmal a providence, ſo afflictive a ſtroke, as now it is, having ſo long a way to run, and ſo many difficulties to go through, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we ſee our ſeveral Homes. This was the cauſe of <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s ſo long, and ſo great <hi>Mourning</hi> for <hi>Moſes, Deut.</hi> 34. <hi>ver.</hi> 8. <hi>And the Children of</hi> Iſrael <hi>wept for</hi> Moſes, <hi>in the Plains of</hi> Moab, <hi>Thirty days. So the days of Weeping and Mourning for</hi> Moſes <hi>were ended.</hi> Mark it, they were yet in the Plains of <hi>Moab;</hi> had they been in quiet, and full poſſeſſion of the Land of <hi>Canaan;</hi> the preſent diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation of <hi>Moſes</hi> his Death (though at any time bitter enough) had not been ſo dreadful, and diſmal to them. But this highly heightned their <hi>Miſery,</hi> and conſequently their <hi>Sorrow,</hi> that he was taken from them, before he had brought them to the promiſed Reſt: So now in this caſe, Oh! what cauſe have we to <hi>Mourn</hi> in an exceeding great meaſure; for that Death has removed our Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian, ſo long before the concluſion of the Voyage.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Conſider, he is taken away whilſt the Judgment of God is upon us, in retarding our Paſſage, and threatning no leſs than a Winter Voyage. We have ſtaid ſo long in the <hi>Indies,</hi> that there is little likelyhood of our going Home this Year. And at preſent, we are here ſcorching in an hot ſultry Climate; the Winds ſo croſs to us, that we can neither go backward or forward; and what will become of us, the Lord knows: But ſure I am, the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:37946:21"/>hand of his Diſpleaſure is ſtretched out againſt us; and we feel in part, that terrible Word threatned, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26. <hi>ver.</hi> 31. <hi>Then ſaid Jeſus unto them, All ye ſhall be offended becauſe of me this night: for it is written, I will ſmite the Sheapherd, and the Sheep of the Flock ſhall be ſcattered abroad.</hi> Ah! Sirs, Death has ſmitten our Phyſitian, and we arc like to be <hi>ſcattered abroad:</hi> God Almighty knows where we may be forced to Winter; where we may be driven for ſhelter from the Furious Ocean, we cannot as yet tell: But the great, yea certain likelyhood of our being Toſſed up and down the World for ſeveral Months, before we can get about <hi>Cape of good Hope,</hi> makes this Loſs the more conſiderable, and our Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the more lamentable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Conſider, he is taken away in his Youthful days, yea, in the very flower of his Youth, in the height and excellency of his Strength. We ought to be <hi>Mourners in the Street,</hi> when we ſee any Man go to his <hi>Long Home;</hi> but to ſee a Young Man go there, that's newly come into the World: That is beginning (as it were) to live; that is, but bloſſoming in the early Spring of his Years—to ſee ſuch an one ſo immaturely ſeized upon by the griping paw of Death: Oh! this muſt needs aggravate Sorrow very greatly. Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this account it was, that there was made ſuch an heavy Lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation for the Death of <hi>Joſiah,</hi> that Famous: King of <hi>Judah,</hi> 2 Chron. 35. ver. 24, 25. <hi>His ſervants therefore took him out of that Chariot, and put him in the ſecond Chariot that he had, and they brought him to</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>and he Dyed, and was Buried in one of the Sepulchers of his Fathers; and all</hi> Judah, <hi>and</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>Mourned for</hi> Joſiah. <hi>And</hi> Jeremiah <hi>Lamented for</hi> Joſiah, <hi>and all the Singing Men, and the Sing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Women, ſpake of</hi> Joſiah <hi>in their Lamentations to this day, and made them an Ordinance in</hi> Iſrael; <hi>and behold they are written in the Lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations.</hi> He had not Lived out half his days, but was unexſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly taken off from farther doing of Good; and this made them Lament ſo ſorely over him: And the ſame cauſe have we to La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment this day, for this our Deceaſed Friend, who, contrary to the thoughts and expectations of us all, was on a ſudden ſnatched from us, before he had arrived to the Thirtyeth Year of his Age. He was an healthy ſtrong Man. I remember not above two days before he ſickned, he was Jocoſely telling me, he looked upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf as the moſt healthy and likelieſt Man to Live in the Ship. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed I thought he was: But Ah! how ſoon was he gone! A little
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:37946:22"/>ſickneſs carryed him away. Lord, <hi>How vain a thing is Man!</hi> How ſubject to Fade and Periſh in his ſtrongeſt, and moſt advantagious ſtate. I will not ſay of our Friend, as <hi>Virgil</hi> ſaid of his <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenas,</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Longius annoſo vivere dignus avo.</q>
            <p>But 'twas pity (had it been the Will of God) that a few Years more had not been added to his Life: And his being ſo untimely removed, beſpake our greater Lamentation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Conſider, he is taken away in the midſt of deſires, and wiſhes for his Life. If Prayers, if Tears, if Endeavors of all ſorts, could have laved his Life, this Sorrowfull and Mournful day had not been. 'Tis a great Judgment for a Man to Live undeſired, and to Dye unlamented: And hence, when the Lord would expreſs his Anger to <hi>Jchoiakim</hi> for his wickedneſs, he threatens him with this Judgment, <hi>Jer.</hi> 22. <hi>ver.</hi> 18, 19. <hi>Therefore thus ſaith the Lord con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning</hi> Jchoiakim <hi>the Son of</hi> Joſiah <hi>King of</hi> Judah, <hi>they ſhall not La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for him, ſaying, Ah! my Brother; or Ah! my Siſter; they ſhall not Lament for him, ſaying, Ah! Lord; or Ah! his Glory. He ſhall be buryed with the Eurial of an</hi> Aſſe, <hi>drawn and caſt forth beyond the Gates of</hi> Jeruſalem. But it is not ſo with our Friend. I am conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent not a Perſon here, but does really Lament his Death. I ſee the Characters of Sorrow engraven in all your Faces. I know you Loved him Living, and now Dead, you are Mourners for him And I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e farther <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, had your Sorrow been as Effectual, as it was Cordial, you had prevented his Deceaſe. So that, <hi>Hand o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus eſt Calearibus.</hi> There's no need of any Spurs to your Lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, that Labor is happily obviated. I have indeed been ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you, for your Satisfaction and Conſolation, the juſt grounds of your Sorrow, to ſecure you from the imputation of Irrational. I ſhall now conclude, only with a few words, to put your Sorrow in the right Channel; that you <hi>may ſorrow</hi> (as the Apoſtle phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes it) <hi>after a Godly ſort.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Mourn for this Loſs by way of Reflection; That is, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect on the condition you might have been in, if God had cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led you to an account for your manifold Sins. Is a Man of ſuch Uſe and Worth taken away ſo ſuddenly by Death from us; Oh! How ſhould we Fear and Tremble, to think what will become of us, who are of ſo little Uſe in the World, who have lived unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitably, and unfruitfully all our days; who have done little or no
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:37946:22"/>good, in the ſeveral Capacities we have been. How ſhould it alſo incite us to a ſpeedy and unfeigned <hi>Repentance,</hi> leſt a worſe Death come upon us; according to the advice of our bleſſed Lord, <hi>Luke</hi> 13. <hi>ver.</hi> 2, 3. <hi>And Jeſus anſwering, ſaid unto them, Suppoſe ye that theſe</hi> Galileans <hi>were ſinners above all the</hi> Galileans, <hi>becauſe they ſuffered ſuch things? I tell ye nay: but except ye repent, ye ſhall all likewiſe periſh.</hi> Oh! Sirs, do you think, that this our dear and worthy Brother was a Sinner above all of us; becauſe he is gone down into the ſhades of Death before us? <hi>I tell you nay, but except you and I repent, we ſhall all likewiſe periſh.</hi> Oh! Therefore I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you, let this ſad providence be a loud call to <hi>Repentance</hi> and <hi>Reformation;</hi> and to ſay with the Church—<hi>Come, let us turn to the Lord, for he hath torn, and he will heal us; he hath ſmitten, and he will bind us up.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Mourn for this Loſs by way of Humiliation. Oh! la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor to be ſo ſenſible of this ſad Stroke, as to be humbled under it; and to lye low before the Lord, who hath ſo ſorely viſited us in this moſt grievous manner. Humiliation is the great expected, and deſigned End of Correction. God led his antient People through the Wilderneſs, and exerciſed them with manifold Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, that he might humble them, and conſequently do them good in their <hi>latter end.</hi> 'Tis ſign of an hardned, and obdurate Heart induced, when there is no humbling under the mighty Hand of God: And Reprobate-Silver ſhall Men call them, that are not Reſined in the Fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ce of Affliction. 'Twas ſpoken as an horrid Aggravation of <hi>Iſraels</hi> Iniquity, and Impenitency, that after all the Laſhes and Scourges of God's Rod, and all his proceedings in way of Judgment againſt them: <hi>Yet</hi> (ſays the Text) <hi>they are not humbled even unto this day.</hi> Ah! Sirs, How Lamentably would our Sins be heightned, how exceedingly would our Souls be ripened for Deſtruction; if we ſhould not be humbled under this preſent aw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Diſpenſation! For verily, the Lord is riſen up, as in Mount <hi>Perizim:</hi> He is Wroth, as in the Valley of <hi>Gideon;</hi> and is doing his Work, his ſtrange Work; and is bringing to paſs his Act, his ſtrange Act; in viſiting our Tranſgreſſions with this ſmarting Rod; and our Iniquities with this wounding Stripe! And ſhall we ſay, the Shadow of the Mountain; and make but a light thing of it? Oh! God forbid! But rather I beſeech you, let us (whilſt our Spirits are dejected by this Loſs) endeavor to have our hearts
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:37946:23"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:37946:23"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:37946:24"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:37946:24"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:37946:25"/>humbled in the Sence of the Lord's anger, that he may not farther be provoked to bring worſe evils and calamities upon us. How was <hi>David</hi> humbled, and melted at the News of the Death of <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Jonathan?</hi> How did he brake forth into this bitter Lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1. <hi>ver.</hi> 19. <hi>The beauty of</hi> Iſrael <hi>is ſlain upon thy high places, how are the mighty fallen.</hi> Truly we may juſtly take up the ſame Complaint, in the ſame words, <hi>The beauty of our ſociety, the glory of our company, the excellency of our community, is fallen and peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed from among us this day;</hi> which beſpeaks not only Heart-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition, but Soul-humiliation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Mourn for this Loſs, by way of ſubmiſſion, and reſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of your Wills, to the good Will and Pleaſure of Almighty God; and ceaſing to murmur or complain, becauſe that he has done it. We ſhould ſay of this Diſpenſation, as the <hi>Magicians</hi> ſaid of the Lice, <hi>Exod.</hi> 8. <hi>ver.</hi> 19. <hi>Then the</hi> Magicians <hi>ſaid unto</hi> Pharaoh, <hi>This is the finger of God: And</hi> Pharaoh's <hi>heart was hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and he hearkned not unto them, as the Lord had ſaid.</hi> Oh! Sirs, we ſhould ſay, this is the handy work of God, of that God, <hi>Whoſe Judgments are unſearchable, and whoſe Ways are paſt finding out:</hi> and therefore we ought, with all holy filial Reverence, to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to what he has done.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Oh! Mourn for this Loſs, by way of preparations, for your own turn, whenſoever it ſhall pleaſe God to call you to it. This was <hi>Moſes</hi> his wiſh for <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and it is mine for you, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32. <hi>ver.</hi> 29. <hi>O that they were wiſe, that they knew this, that they would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider their Latter End.</hi> So to conſider of it, as to prepare for it. And eſpecially to conſider of it, when we ſee others taken away from among us. Oh! How ſhould Objects of Mortality before us, be as preſſing Lectures of Divinity to us, to put us in mind of the certainty of our own Dying, and the neceſſary prae-requiſites to a Dying State; that when we come to the Borders of Death, inſtead of fearing it, we may ſarcaſmally triumph over it in the words of the bleſſed Apoſtle, <hi>O Death, where is thy Sting,? O Grave, where is thy Victory?</hi> And when (like <hi>Aaron</hi> upon Mount <hi>Hor</hi>) we are ſtrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped of the Robes of Mortality, we may be inveſted with the more beauteous and tranſcendent Garment of everlaſting Glory in our Fathers Houſe, where are many Manſions, to enjoy the Soul-ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhing Communion of bleſſed Saints and Angels in the higheſt Heaven; to ſit under the ſhadow of our Glorified <hi>Lord Jeſus</hi> with
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:37946:25"/>great delight, and to have his Fruit for ever pleaſant to our Taſt, wrapt up in the Joys and Conſolations of the Spirit, waiting for that one only additional Happineſs, even the Adoption; to wit, the Redemption of the Body. In a word, to be with our own God; the God of all Peace and Comfort, in whoſe Preſence there is fulneſs of Joy, and at whoſe Right Hand there are Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures for evermore.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="elegy">
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:37946:26"/>
            <head>AN ELEGY On the Death of the before-Named Mr. <hi>Rich, Bernard,</hi> Conſecrated to his MEMORY, BY ONE Who Loved him Dearly, Prized him Highly, And Laments him Greatly.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>AN Grief be ſilent! Rather, can Grief ſpeak!</l>
               <l>A Top-full Veſſel ſcarce finds vent to Leak.</l>
               <l>Hearts that are charg'd, and over-preſs'd with Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row,</l>
               <l>Deny to lend what <hi>Mourning Tongues</hi> would borrow.</l>
               <l>Words may be form'd in ſaddeſt caſe, no doubt;</l>
               <l>But Sighs and Groans will ſtop their paſſage out.</l>
               <l>Wonder not then we are ſo Mute, even now,</l>
               <l>Our Souls to Grief's moſt rigid Laws we bow.</l>
               <l>And in the Duſt ſeem liveleſs as we lye,</l>
               <l>True Hieroglyphicks of our Miſery;</l>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:37946:26"/>
               <l>Senſe of our Loſs, deprives us of all Senſe,</l>
               <l>We more than Maſters in Griefs-School Commence:</l>
               <l>Like Weeping <hi>Niobes</hi> we are become,</l>
               <l>Grief makes us ſad, but Horror ſtrikes us dumb!</l>
               <l>Our Tongues can't Accent, what our Hearts direct,</l>
               <l>Deep Groans and Sobs muſt be our Dialect!</l>
               <l>We'll Sob his Death, and with an Heart-fetch'd Groan,</l>
               <l>That Loſs (which ne're can be repair'd) make known.</l>
               <l>A Loſs indeed, beyond a Vulgar Loſs,</l>
               <l>As far, as <hi>Ophir</hi> pureſt Gold's from Droſs:</l>
               <l>Death hath not ſnatched one of our common Friends,</l>
               <l>But one, in whom the Life of Friendſhip ends.</l>
               <l>The Soul of Love, the Quinteſcence of Mirth,</l>
               <l>Whoſe preſence mid-wiv'd Joy into a Birth;</l>
               <l>Who Lov'd, and knew to blow (where e're he came)</l>
               <l>The Sparks of Pleaſure to an open Flame:</l>
               <l>So Apprehenſive, half-Ey'd Men might ſee,</l>
               <l>He was ingenious to a Prodigie.</l>
               <l>His rare and great Accompliſhments inhanc'd</l>
               <l>His Price, above all Value; and Advanc'd</l>
               <l>Th' admir'd Capacity of his known Name,</l>
               <l>To cope the glory of <hi>Machaons</hi> Fame:</l>
               <l>In all the Rules of Phyſick he excell'd,</l>
               <l>And very hardly to be Parallell'd.</l>
               <l>Diſeaſes own'd his Power, and Heaven did Bleſs</l>
               <l>His Skill to moſt, with wonderful Succeſs.</l>
               <l>Beſides all this, he had a greater Art,</l>
               <l>To feel the Pulſe of a Diſtemper'd Heart;</l>
               <l>And by his Candid Carriage to unty,</l>
               <l>The Gordian-Knot of inward Miſery:</l>
               <l>His Wit and Parts, diſpell'd the Clouds of Sadneſs,</l>
               <l>And changed Sorrow into peals of Gladneſs.</l>
               <l>Judge, judge how <hi>Mournful</hi> now is our Condition,</l>
               <l>That thus have loſt a Duplicate-Phyſitian.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Well might the Cannons roar when he was gone,</l>
               <l>The fitteſt Emblem of our general Moan;</l>
               <l>They were our Organs, thorough which we broke</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Griefs</hi> deadly ſilence, and in Thunder ſpoke:</l>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:37946:27"/>
               <l>We ſent (by them) our loud-mouth'd doleful Cryes,</l>
               <l>Reſounding <hi>Woe</hi> and <hi>Horror</hi> to the Skyes.</l>
               <l>The Air was black with Smoke, to let us ſee,</l>
               <l>That Element did <hi>Mourn</hi> as well as we:</l>
               <l>The Sea did <hi>Foam, <hi>Neptune</hi>
                  </hi> was full of Fears,</l>
               <l>Leſt he ſhould ſhake his Kingdom 'bout his Ears.</l>
               <l>And in our Fury riſe to ſuch a paſs,</l>
               <l>As to attempt the wreſting of his Mace;</l>
               <l>For having rob'd us of ſo rich a Jem,</l>
               <l>More-priz'd by us, than all his Diadem.</l>
               <l>We needed not his Water for a Grave</l>
               <l>Unto our Friend, each Tear more than a Wave</l>
               <l>Would ſoon have ſwel'd into a Sea for him,</l>
               <l>And been enough for th' Coffin in't to Swim:</l>
               <l>Or rather ſink true Sorrow's ſuch a freight</l>
               <l>To poize down more, than many Thouſand Weight</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I now deſpiſe great <hi>Aeolus,</hi> and his ſtorms,</l>
               <l>Though repreſented in tremendious forms.</l>
               <l>The raging of the Seas henceforth no more,</l>
               <l>Shall fright my Soul, thought Winds and Waves do roar;</l>
               <l>Now he is there whoſe influencing charms,</l>
               <l>Keep back their fury from inflicting harms;</l>
               <l>And by his Art and Skill right Chymical,</l>
               <l>Makes all their Waters more than Med'cinal</l>
               <l>'Twas often ſaid, <hi>The Sea abounds in Store</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>More than the Earth,</hi> I nere believ'd before;</l>
               <l>But now I ſhall, and readily ſubmit</l>
               <l>With all my heart, unto the Truth of it;</l>
               <l>Since ſo much Learning, Parts, and Worth, is in't,</l>
               <l>What can it be leſs, than a peerleſs Mint?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Here ſtop my Pen, no farther 'tempt to build</l>
               <l>Statues of <hi>Mourning</hi> in this ſable Field:</l>
               <l>Call for the Epilogue, draw out the Screene,</l>
               <l>And put Concluſion to this doleful Scene.</l>
               <l>The Floods of Tears which from our Eyes have run,</l>
               <l>With Sighs he's wafted to <hi>Eliſium.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="elegy">
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:37946:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Epitaph.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Arewel dear Heart, thy abſence makes me ſad,</l>
               <l>The trueſt Friend that ever Mortal had.</l>
               <l>My pleaſant Sea-Conſort, the very Soul,</l>
               <l>Of that delight, which Sadneſs does Controul:</l>
               <l>My Boſom-Friend, to whom I could diſpence,</l>
               <l>The greateſt Secrets with ſafe-Confidence.</l>
               <l>My Counſellor, with whom I could adviſe,</l>
               <l>And learn by Imitation, to be Wiſe:</l>
               <l>A Brother dearer, than by Nature can,</l>
               <l>In Life and Death, to me a <hi>Jonathan.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Reſt, reſt in Peace within thy Watry-Urn,</l>
               <l>Whilſt I toſs'd up and down, ſhall Sigh and Mourn,</l>
               <l>To think of my great Loſs, in loſing Thee,</l>
               <l>Once happy in thy ſweet Society.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What! Art thou Dead? My thought my Dream was ſo.</l>
               <l>Ah! 'tis too true a Dream: the more the Woe.</l>
               <l>Thou hadſt thy Plea, though cam'ſt unto thy Tryal;</l>
               <l>Death was thy Judge, and would have no Denyal.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Charles Nicholettes.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
